<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://micahmartin.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-05-01T19:51:52-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com//</id><title type="html">OneX Build Log</title><subtitle>I'm building an airplane.  This is how it went so far.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Tight Quarters</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/01/tight-quarters.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tight Quarters" /><published>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/01/tight-quarters</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/01/tight-quarters.html">&lt;p&gt;The tail is attached!  It all began last Friday.  Christoph, a colleague from 8th Light in London was in town for a conference.  After we flew to Sedona for lunch I convinced him to help me attach the tail surfaces to the fuselage.  We tried out the vertical tail and with a little finagling, got the gist of it figured out, though we didn’t fasten anything yet.  Then we tried on the horizontal tail and this is where it hit the fan.  It wasn’t fitting, at all.  The bottom skin was too long.  Then Christoph asked “Is it possible that the skin is up side down?”  Fear overtook me.  I checked the plans, made some measurements, and realized the truth. I had installed it upside down!  How could it be?  I checked them several times before installing and even wrote on the skins in sharpie to identify which way was up and which was was down.  Some how I got them backwards.  The horror!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this such a big deal?  The skin is held on with around 250 rivets.  Reversing it means drilling out all the rivits, flipping the skins and installing 250 new rivets.  As we’ve learned, rivets don’t always come out nicely.  If I could drill 9 out of 10 rivets successfully, which would be pretty good, that’d leave 25 wrecked rivet holes, not to mention hours of effort. The upside is that reversing the skins is possible because other than the slight difference in length where they meet the fuselage, that are symmetrical top to bottom. But I felt like crying.  Christoph and I called it a day and got some beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day I drove out to Deer Valley airport to fly with Denny (other OneX builder) in his RV-12.  He did a great job building that plane and we had a very nice flight.  But the point is that on the drive there and back I figured out a solution to my horizontal tail skins.  First, I could cut the bottom side (which was supposed to the top) to fit.  This would leave a 1/2 inch gap on the top.  But I had already considered crafting some fairings.  We learned a technique to make fairings out of composite materials (fiberglass) in the EAA workshops I went to in Las Vegas.  Not only would this cover the gap, but it would also make the plane more aerodynamic!  Double win!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I cut the skins to size.  Christoph helped me file it down, then file it some more, and again until it fit perfectly.  It turns out that had I installed the skins properly we would have had to file away a good bit of material anyway.  In the end, there was only a minor gap on the front top side, maybe 1/4 inch.  This was all very relieving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I continued fastening the tail surfaces, and I’m just about done.  That tail section is tight!  It has been very challenging to get the nuts on and tightened because nothing is directly accessible.  I was constantly reaching through inspection holes and between parts, and half the time my socket wrench was useless because it wouldn’t fit.  I had to go buy second set of wrenches to get it done.  And Luka had to come and help me reach parts that were impossible for me and my fat hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still work to be done here but I think the worst parts are done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-01/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Christoph With Tail&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-01/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Attached&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">The tail is attached!  It all began last Friday.  Christoph, a colleague from 8th Light in London was in town for a conference.  After we flew to Sedona for lunch I convinced him to help me attach the tail surfaces to the fuselage.  We tried out the vertical tail and with a little finagling, got the gist of it figured out, though we didn’t fasten anything yet.  Then we tried on the horizontal tail and this is where it hit the fan.  It wasn’t fitting, at all.  The bottom skin was too long.  Then Christoph asked “Is it possible that the skin is up side down?”  Fear overtook me.  I checked the plans, made some measurements, and realized the truth. I had installed it upside down!  How could it be?  I checked them several times before installing and even wrote on the skins in sharpie to identify which way was up and which was was down.  Some how I got them backwards.  The horror!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dimple Debacle</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/27/dimple-debacle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dimple Debacle" /><published>2017-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/27/dimple-debacle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/27/dimple-debacle.html">&lt;p&gt;Three trips to the hardware store today.  The first was to Ace to get a thread tap to make a threaded hole in the bellcrannk faces.  Those are done. They’re for translating control inputs from the inside part of the wing to the outside, and they’re pretty nifty.  Remeber the wings fold up.  There’s a outboard set of paddles and an inbourd set of paddles.  They lines up with eachother on a swivel.  When one rotates, it pushes the other making it rotate.  See the first pic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debacle.  Sonex includes two Super Simple Dimple Dies in the kit to dimple surfaces for flush rivets.  There’a big one for 1/8” holes and small one for 3/32” holes.  Basically they are two plates of hard metal. When you squeeze them together tightly with the sheet metal in the middle, they bend a little dimple in the sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each set comes with two nails that go through the center so that you can pull them together with a rivet puller.  The small set has skinny nails, understandably.  The first one broke on the first hole I dimpled.  It’s a lot of force required to bend the metal.  The second got me 6 more dimples and broke on the 7th. But it allowed me to finish the wheel pants connectors.  Today I had to dimple the tail mount to install some bolt plates, but I was out of skinny nails; specifically 4D-2” nails.  Earlier in the week I checked at the local Ace and they didn’t have any.  This moring I called Fountain Hill’s Ace and they told me they had two boxes in stock.  So I went over there (2nd trip of the day), but they didn’t have them.  The guys at the store concluded that their manufactureer just didn’t make 4D-2” nails, at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found some music wire that was the right diameter and is really strong, figuring we could bend a head on one end and cut it to length.  I got home and tried it out, several times.  It didn’t work.  The wire, strong as it was, would bend, or snap at the point where I bent a head on it.  My 3rd trip was to Home Depot to see if they had the 4D-2” nails.  They didn’t.  I bought a high temp map blow torch insted.  This allowed me to play blacksmith, hammering the hot wire against my vice making very creative bends.  They all snapped off.  Then I tried the simplest thing.  With red hot wire tip, I just smashed it flat. That worked.  &lt;em&gt;whew&lt;/em&gt;!  You can see all the attempts and the dimple dies in the second pic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third pic is the application of the dimples to attach those nut plates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-27/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bellcranks&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-27/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nail Fails&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-27/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Mount&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Three trips to the hardware store today.  The first was to Ace to get a thread tap to make a threaded hole in the bellcrannk faces.  Those are done. They’re for translating control inputs from the inside part of the wing to the outside, and they’re pretty nifty.  Remeber the wings fold up.  There’s a outboard set of paddles and an inbourd set of paddles.  They lines up with eachother on a swivel.  When one rotates, it pushes the other making it rotate.  See the first pic.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gear Girl</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/26/gear-girl.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gear Girl" /><published>2017-04-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/26/gear-girl</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/26/gear-girl.html">&lt;p&gt;My wonderful wife helped me today!  Together we installed the main landing gear.  It was a two man job.  I got on my creeper under the plane to drill and install the bolts, while she handed me the bits and put on the nuts from above.  What’s gonna work?  Team work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterward she had to go.  So I tried to figure out what I could work on next, while wating for parts to be delivered.  I decided the engine mount would be simple.  Alas, the bolts are missing from that hardware kit.  Sigh.  I ordered them and started working on the bellcrank, the interesting mechanism that translate controls between the wing segments were they fold.  For today, I got a bunch of angle parts fabricated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-26/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Angelique&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">My wonderful wife helped me today!  Together we installed the main landing gear.  It was a two man job.  I got on my creeper under the plane to drill and install the bolts, while she handed me the bits and put on the nuts from above.  What’s gonna work?  Team work!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Main Gear</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/25/main-gear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Main Gear" /><published>2017-04-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/25/main-gear</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/25/main-gear.html">&lt;p&gt;On to a task for which I have the parts: the main gear.  Based on advise from fellow Sonex builders I upgraded the brakes to Sonex’s AeroConversion hydraulics.  The first pic shows the intimidating amount of parts for the brakes.  To my surprise, it all came together quite simply.  So I attached the tires to the gear frame and then researched how to attach it all to the fusealge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are ten bolts that hold the gear onto the fuselage.  However, that big chunk of aluminum used for the gears (the strut?) doesn’t have any pilot holes. And it’s all curvy, so how do you find the exact center?  Well, I tried a few techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) First I laid a meter stick on top and marked the points where the flat top turned into a curve; where it seperated from the ruler.  The results seemed questionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Second I got a string and measured from each end of the strut, bottom to bottom and over the top.  Folding the string in half gave me center.  This seemed accurate but I noticed the string had some stretch to it.  I became worried that the the string’s elasticity would create an error.  So I looked for another method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) The second picture shows the strut balancing on the tip of aluminum angle. With use of a level to make sure it was pefectly balanced, and a carpenter’s square to make sure it was totally perpendicular, I had the center of gravity.  Since all the brakes and tire parts on each end were identical, I now had the center of the strut.  It matched the string’s measurement.  Turns out technique #1 was not good at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;designs&quot;&gt;Designs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checks out the design concepts my friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://nickmeccia.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;Nick Meccia&lt;/a&gt; did for me.  I love how they make the plane come alive!  I loved Transformers when I was a kid so I suggested a Decepticon theme.  These make me giddy with reminiscent joy.  Tough choice but my favorite is the second, Constructacon design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hydraulic Breaks&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Main Gear Assembly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/01.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design #1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/02.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design #2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/03.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design #3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/04.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design #4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/05.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design #5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">On to a task for which I have the parts: the main gear.  Based on advise from fellow Sonex builders I upgraded the brakes to Sonex’s AeroConversion hydraulics.  The first pic shows the intimidating amount of parts for the brakes.  To my surprise, it all came together quite simply.  So I attached the tires to the gear frame and then researched how to attach it all to the fusealge.

There are ten bolts that hold the gear onto the fuselage.  However, that big chunk of aluminum used for the gears (the strut?) doesn’t have any pilot holes. And it’s all curvy, so how do you find the exact center?  Well, I tried a few techniques.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bolted Box &amp;amp; Missing Hardware</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/24/bolted-box-missing-hardware.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bolted Box &amp; Missing Hardware" /><published>2017-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/24/bolted-box--missing-hardware</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/24/bolted-box-missing-hardware.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;blog-improvements&quot;&gt;Blog Improvements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’llbe the first to adminst that navigating this blog has been burdensome.  So I added some Next/Previous links to each page.  And the home page was getting VERY long, transferring far more bits than needed.  So I paginated the blog listing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog runs on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; using Jekyll.  I had originally tried other blog hosting sites, but with my coding background, working in an IDE and doing source control commits to publish new posts feels oh-so natural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These improvements veer off the treaded path of common Jekyll deployments, which means I had to do some yak shaving to get it all working.  I’m still not confident everything is 100% functional at the moment, but the site should be easier to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sustainable-aviation-symposium&quot;&gt;Sustainable Aviation Symposium&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I flew to San Francisco to attend the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sustainableaviation.org/sas2017/&quot;&gt;SA Symposium&lt;/a&gt;.  The topic is totally in line with my goals in aviation so I had to go.  The people there were incredible.  They had bold visions, ambitious goals, and they were achieving them!  Their long term vision, if I can sum it all up fairly, is to allow you to travel around your local town, county, or even state by going to the local air taxi station (similar to train station, or subway stop), hoping in an automated electric plane, and getting where you want to go faster than anything else can get you there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t bore you with names, but you can see who was there on the site.  I got to meet a lot of cool people.  There’s a pretty picture of Monterey Bay below from my flight back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sonex-progress&quot;&gt;Sonex Progress&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The box is bolted.  Almost 70 bolts went into the fuselage box today.  I could hardly believe it was that many.  But it was.  It took all morning an then some before they were all tightened.  And of course they didn’t all fit right away.  You can see in the first picture that they are packed in pretty tight on the firewall… the picture is just one of four corners like that.  In fact, some of the bolts interfere with each other and special skinny nuts are called for, however I couldn’t find them in the hardware kit.  I called Sonex and Kerry told me that the hardware kit is not complete and I need to go buy my own.  Thanks Kerry! Otherwise the fuselage box is all riveted and I’m ready to move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I referred back to the assembly tree at the front of the plans.  The last big branch of the tree is the wings.  But if I build the wings, I wouldn’t feel comfortable hanging them on a fuselage that is currently resting on saw horsed.  So I looked at the landing gear plans and it looks like that’s the next logical step.  But the tail gear requires that vertical and horizontal stabilizers are installed.  As I begin that assembly, I realize that I’m missing even more hardware from the kit.  In this case I think WBParts game me the wrong nut plates, in addition to Sonex not including the required nut in the kit list.  Grrrr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stuck a rivet in the extra hole I mentioned last week.  It’s a tiny SSC-24 countersunk rivet.  See pic.  I just used the deburring tool a bit more aggressively than normal to create the countersunk hole.  My mind is now at ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those building a OneX, the following hardware list is items that you may be missing too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AN960-10 washers.  Buy at least a 100 of these.  They’re called for all over the place and the kit only includes 20.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MS20464-1032 Fiberlock Thin Nuts.  12 or so.  These are the thin nuts to hopefully solve the interference joints.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MS21047-L4 Anchor Nut (Aircraft spruce: K1000-4). At least 3. The kits included these, but they gave me the wrong ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AN4-7A Bolt.  At least 3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-24/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bolts&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-24/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rivetd Extra Hole&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-24/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Box Rivited&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-24/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monterey Bay&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Blog Improvements</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deburring The Box</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/19/deburring-the-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deburring The Box" /><published>2017-04-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/19/deburring-the-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/19/deburring-the-box.html">&lt;p&gt;I wish I had enough interesting information to blog every day, but despite the last 17 hours of effort over the last two days, I’ve only got one new picture for you.  This is the fuselage box all updrilled, deburred, and ready to rivet/bolt.  Lots of bolts are called out to fasten the box together, which I suppose it for adding extra strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing of interest is that there were some needed holes that were impossible to drill with my hand drill and even the 90° chuck I got.  They are inside the box where the gear braces on the floor meet the vertical beams on the side walls, down in the bottom corner.  In the end I had to go to Home Depot and buy a Milewaukee angle bit that only holds hex bit, so I had to buy all new drill bits with hex ends.  It did the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a bunch of parts in this box assembly.  Over that past few days it was exciting to see the fuselage lengthen and look more and more complete.  And then, just when it all came together and fit perfectly, I had to take it all apart leaving me with just the tail I started with last week.  Onlookers are puzzled by the backward progress.  But I explain it’s a necessary step to prepare each piece for final fastening… and that is a time consuming process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: The plans for the side wall make you think that the skins are missing a pilot hole just below the wing.  When I noticed that I figured the skins pre-dated that plans (Kerry told me that was the case in other instances) so I added the hole.  That was a mistake.  The wing root covers the hole and the typical pop-rivet would cause it to bulge out.  So now I’m left with an extra hole on each side of the box.  It’s only visible from the inside, but I’ll always know it’s there and it’ll bother me forever.  Maybe I can countersink the hole with the deburring tool and put a flush rivet in there to put my mind at ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog entry brings me up to 300 hours of built time.  Only 200 hours left, according to Sonex marketing.  Yeah, right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-19/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Box Ready To Rivet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">I wish I had enough interesting information to blog every day, but despite the last 17 hours of effort over the last two days, I’ve only got one new picture for you.  This is the fuselage box all updrilled, deburred, and ready to rivet/bolt.  Lots of bolts are called out to fasten the box together, which I suppose it for adding extra strength.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Skeleton In The Box</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/17/skeleton-in-the-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Skeleton In The Box" /><published>2017-04-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/17/skeleton-in-the-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/17/skeleton-in-the-box.html">&lt;p&gt;I made all the angles and ribs for the fuselage box.  It’s a matter of assembling them all now.  Not so easy.  All the plans are in 2 dimensions, while the real plane is in three dimensions, obviously.  The plans try to make up for this by showing multiple vantage point such as showing the same assembly from top, side and bottom.  Sometimes that’s just not enough to give all the required details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I called up my Onex builder buddy, Dennis Marick.  He game lots of good tips and offered for me to come visit his build.  That was great.  Just what I needed.  I took a ton of pictures and figured out exactly how the parts are supposed to fit together.  It was also great to just shoot the sh** and compare build notes.  I noticed several things nice about his build… like somehow he got all the turtledeck formers to fit pretty flush with the skin, no fluting or major bending.  Turns out he had a pro builder help him out… maybe I should do that more often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another struggle was that multiple parts of that plans converge at this point.  The page I’m on is “Fuselage Box Assembly”, but that intersects with the firewall, canopy, glare shield, and most pressing: the landing gear.  The bottom cross beams are called out in the landing gear assembly, and there are variants in the plans for tail dragger and tricycle configurations.  It’s unclear which parts I should be working on now, because it sure seems like it’ll be much harder to add more parts here later when everything is riveted and closed up.  And flipping back and forth between three different plan pages is tiresome.  I think I’ve got it figured out now though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the evening I drilled pilot holes for the firewall and got that clecoed on.  Still much to do here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-17/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Skelton&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-17/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Firewall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">I made all the angles and ribs for the fuselage box.  It’s a matter of assembling them all now.  Not so easy.  All the plans are in 2 dimensions, while the real plane is in three dimensions, obviously.  The plans try to make up for this by showing multiple vantage point such as showing the same assembly from top, side and bottom.  Sometimes that’s just not enough to give all the required details.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Framing the Box</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/13/framing-the-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Framing the Box" /><published>2017-04-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/13/framing-the-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/13/framing-the-box.html">&lt;p&gt;The box floor is drilled and clecoed to the walls.  All three of those parts are clecoed to the tail.  Now there are a dozen or so beams and angles to add strength and rigidity to the structure.  That means more sawing, grinding, and polishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second picture you can see the seat attach beam that goes across the floor skin, with some piano hinge on the back and two little arms that get riveted to the side longerons.  This one took a couple hours to make but it fits in it’s spot perfectly.  I was able to grab my creeper from my hangar at Scottdale the other day which was a good thing; it allowed me to slide underneath and drill from the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the front gear brace, 3rd picture.  This is cut from a hefty chunk of aluminum.  It’s 2” x 2” extruded angle, 3/16th inches think.  That’s more thank twice as thick as the typical angle parts required.  It gave my band saw a workout.  I spent a good amount of time filing it and polishing it to make it smooth and shiny.  It too fit perfectly.  Then I went back to the plans and noticed that three these gear braces are required.  Back to the bandsaw to make two more…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-13/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Box Sides&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-13/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Seat Brace&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-13/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gear Brace&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">The box floor is drilled and clecoed to the walls.  All three of those parts are clecoed to the tail.  Now there are a dozen or so beams and angles to add strength and rigidity to the structure.  That means more sawing, grinding, and polishing.

In the second picture you can see the seat attach beam that goes across the floor skin, with some piano hinge on the back and two little arms that get riveted to the side longerons.  This one took a couple hours to make but it fits in it’s spot perfectly.  I was able to grab my creeper from my hangar at Scottdale the other day which was a good thing; it allowed me to slide underneath and drill from the bottom.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Turtledeck Finished</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/11/turtledeck-finished.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turtledeck Finished" /><published>2017-04-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/11/turtledeck-finished</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/11/turtledeck-finished.html">&lt;p&gt;First, I took apart the whole turtledeck assembly.  I deburred and cleaned all the parts, reassembled everything, and riveted, and riveted some more.  Finally, it’s all done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some minor indentations from rivets where the interior formers didn’t push all the way up to the skin.  Despite my efforts in prep, I didn’t seem to get the formers to stretch all the way out to the skin.  There was a half inch gap in some cases before I bent them down to 1/8” gaps.  It could have been much worse.  I’m not too worries because, one, they are minor, and two, I believe I can fill them with micro balloons before painting so none will know.  Come to think of it, my Piper Archer had indentations at rivet locations too… so maybe it’s fairly normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to the fuselage box.  This is an involved step in the plans.  And for the first time, it calls out for parts further ahead in the plans.  I started by lining up the sides with the fuselage tail.  At first it seemed to fit perfectly.  But then I noticed that holes in parts already fastened to the tail didn’t line up exactly with the those on the box sides.  Hmmmm.  It could be I bent parts too much or installed them wrong… but I’m pretty sure all my bends were right on, and all of these parts had pilot holes so I couldn’t have installed them wrong.  Perhaps this it’s normal that two complext parts don’t fit perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I resorted to dilling the holes again.  In some cases, it made the holes slightly bigger.  That’s not a problem because I’ll be updrilling anyway.  In other cases, the holes turned into ovals, or figure 8s, or even an adjacent hole.  I’ll have to address these case by case and add reinforcement plates if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was confusing to proceed without the floor inplace so I removed the side panels, turned them upside down and drilled out the holes for the floor.  Then my time was up for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-11/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Turtledeck Finished&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-11/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fuselage Box Begun&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">First, I took apart the whole turtledeck assembly.  I deburred and cleaned all the parts, reassembled everything, and riveted, and riveted some more.  Finally, it’s all done.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Turtle Deck Take 2</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/10/turtle-deck-take-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turtle Deck Take 2" /><published>2017-04-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/10/turtle-deck-take-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/10/turtle-deck-take-2.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I got started on the new turtle deck skins.  The first step is to attach them to the splice channel.  You can see them in the first picture all cleanup up and ready to rivet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sonex built such a nice crate to ship the skins that I felt bad destroying it.  And I needed more table top space so I sawed it in half and made a table out of it.  See second pic.  That floor space where the engine sits was unusable but now it’s highly functional.  It’s just a temporary table that I’ll depose of at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my new understanding of the turtle deck assembly instructions, things went MUCH smoother.  It’s still a good deal of work, and I had to make some tweaks.  For example, the front formers… they attach to the front of the splice channel but it was too long and the formers were protruding from the skins.  So I cut off the end and made a new one.  And the former flanges don’t fit perfectly with the curve of the skins so it took quite a bit of bending and fluting to make a tight fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, however, all of the formers and skins are installed and updrilled without any dents or kinks.  Now I just need to take it all apart, debur, clean and reinstall before riveting.  Fingers crossed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, while installing the turtledeck skins, I realized that it would be near impossible to reach some of the holes for the bulkheads after the turtledeck was in place.  That led me to do a bunch of riveting that I’d been postponing.  All the bulkheads and other fuselage parts are now riveted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-10/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New Turtledeck Skins&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-10/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crate Table&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-10/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inital Turtledeck Install&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-10/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Turtledeck Updrilled&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Yesterday, I got started on the new turtle deck skins.  The first step is to attach them to the splice channel.  You can see them in the first picture all cleanup up and ready to rivet.</summary></entry></feed>
