<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://micahmartin.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-05-17T22:18:39-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com//</id><title type="html">OneX Build Log</title><subtitle>I'm building an airplane.  This is how it went so far.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Place to Sit</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/17/a-place-to-sit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Place to Sit" /><published>2017-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/17/a-place-to-sit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/17/a-place-to-sit.html">&lt;p&gt;Lots to report:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wrap&quot;&gt;Wrap&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a test for going the vinyl wrap route as apposed to paint, I decided to wrap the hood of my car to get a feel for the process.  I got Luka to help me.  There was a learning curve.  It actually took us three attempts over 2 weeks and we ruined two wraps.  I had to order a new one with each failed attempt.  But in the end we got it as you can see in the first pic.  The carbon fiber texture and anthracite color is subtle, which is how I wanted it.&lt;br /&gt;
Lesson learned:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t stress about bubbles.  The 3M vinyl actually breathes allowing you to push bubbles out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peel off the backing while the wrap is upside down.  With your partner, flip it, gently stretch it and lay it down to cover the surface.  Getting the general layout right and smooth on the first try goes a long way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t over work the vinyl.  I found that it weakens as you work it.  Eventually it rips.  That’s bad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use a heat gun to restore the vinyls shape and integrity.  It’s cool material.  It remembers it’s shape.  So when it get’s stretched, maybe by your fingers, heat it and it will morph back into it’s original shape.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Watch lots of youtube videos.  There’s tons of techniques to learn from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-17/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wrapped Hood&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;spar-ends&quot;&gt;Spar Ends&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ends of the spars have several parts that get bolted on.  See second picture.  Of course hardware is missing from the kit so I had to order more from Aircraft Spruce.  Unbelievably I ran our of washers. The kit came with 20, FAR too few.  I ordered 150 more a few weeks ago.  But that still wasn’t enough so I ordered 400 more.  For now, most of the bolts are in place.   I’ll have to revisit this to put washers in place and swap out some bolts for the correct ones that are on order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-17/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spar Ends&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-seat&quot;&gt;A Seat&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was fun.  Once the seat was installed I couldn’t help but to jump in and try it out.  I just chilled for a few minutes in the half finished cockpit.  Although it looks tiny from the outside, it feels rather spacious on the inside.  Luka and Tristan tried it out too when they got back from school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-17/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tristan In Plane&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-17/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Luka In Plane&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;flap-retainer&quot;&gt;Flap Retainer&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This intricate part was a challenge to fabricate.  I will hold the flap lever, which has yet to be installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-17/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Flap Retainer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Lots to report:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rough Riveting</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/15/rough-riveting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rough Riveting" /><published>2017-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/15/rough-riveting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/15/rough-riveting.html">&lt;p&gt;All the solid rivets in the main spar have been bucked.  I can honestly say that I prefer the pull rivets over the solid rivets any day.  Why?  Bucking rivets is strenuous.  I began on Friday and it started fun.  But after a few dozen, my elbow was sore from holding the bucking bar, and I had a blister on hand from the hammer.  The hammer is a nice pneumatic gun, but all those impacts that their toll.  I had to quit after a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I recruited Luka and his friend Caleb to help me by holding the bucking bar.  After a few botched rivets, we got the hang of working together but time was tight and we only got about 100 rivets bucked before time ran out.  There are over 300 in the main spar. So I continued today and toughed it out until they were all done.  Whew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason the rivets that went through the angles, at the top and bottom, took much much longer to buck.  Maybe 5 time more blows with the hammer.  Where the angle tappered out, they got easy again.  Not sure why.  There must be something about the angles that absorbs the impacts, leaving less energy to squeeze the rivets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once complete, I managed to slide the spar into place.  This was no easy task either.  It required filing edges and some brute force with a rubber mallet to get it into place.  I was careful not to damage anything and in the end it fit nicely.  The brackets that attach the spar to the fuselage are in the works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-15/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spare in Plane&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-15/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First Rivets&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-15/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rivetted Spar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">All the solid rivets in the main spar have been bucked.  I can honestly say that I prefer the pull rivets over the solid rivets any day.  Why?  Bucking rivets is strenuous.  I began on Friday and it started fun.  But after a few dozen, my elbow was sore from holding the bucking bar, and I had a blister on hand from the hammer.  The hammer is a nice pneumatic gun, but all those impacts that their toll.  I had to quit after a while.

On Sunday I recruited Luka and his friend Caleb to help me by holding the bucking bar.  After a few botched rivets, we got the hang of working together but time was tight and we only got about 100 rivets bucked before time ran out.  There are over 300 in the main spar. So I continued today and toughed it out until they were all done.  Whew.

For some reason the rivets that went through the angles, at the top and bottom, took much much longer to buck.  Maybe 5 time more blows with the hammer.  Where the angle tappered out, they got easy again.  Not sure why.  There must be something about the angles that absorbs the impacts, leaving less energy to squeeze the rivets.

Once complete, I managed to slide the spar into place.  This was no easy task either.  It required filing edges and some brute force with a rubber mallet to get it into place.  I was careful not to damage anything and in the end it fit nicely.  The brackets that attach the spar to the fuselage are in the works.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Dilled, I Deburred…</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/11/i-dilled-i-deburred.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Dilled, I Deburred..." /><published>2017-05-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/11/i-dilled-i-deburred</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/11/i-dilled-i-deburred.html">&lt;p&gt;I drilled.  I deburred.  I got a repetitive stress injury.  At least I suspect I am.  It’s the deburring.  It puts a lot of pressure on the center of my palm and I think it’s the cause of a loss of sensitivity in my fingers in the last couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the spar, well most of it, all drilled and ready for deburring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps tomorrow I’ll get to solid rivets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-11/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spar All Drilled&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">I drilled.  I deburred.  I got a repetitive stress injury.  At least I suspect I am.  It’s the deburring.  It puts a lot of pressure on the center of my palm and I think it’s the cause of a loss of sensitivity in my fingers in the last couple of months.

Below is the spar, well most of it, all drilled and ready for deburring.

Perhaps tomorrow I’ll get to solid rivets.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Spar is a Bear</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/10/this-spar-is-a-bear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Spar is a Bear" /><published>2017-05-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/10/this-spar-is-a-bear</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/10/this-spar-is-a-bear.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday… I tried to decipher the plans and figure out how all the inboard spar pieces fit together.  In my head I had expected the spar to be just one or two long pieces of beefy metal.  Not so.  There’s got to be thirty pieces or so.  Once assembled they essentially form one long beefy chunk of metal, but with intricacies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I emailed Kerry and asked for pictures to help be understand.  He sent me some, but what really helped what a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onexmike.org/spar--inboard.html&quot;&gt;blog from a guy I know as Onex Mike&lt;/a&gt;.  This spelled it out for me with just the right pictures.  Thank Mike!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onces that was figured out, I had to drill holes in all the ribs, beams, supports and other stuff.  I finally finished today.  The shear quantity of material in this spar multiplies the work.  I’ll sheepishly admit that I thought I’d be done with the spar in a day or so.  Oh well.  One step after another. The picture below is the clecoed spar ready to updrill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-10/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inboard Spar, Clecoed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Yesterday… I tried to decipher the plans and figure out how all the inboard spar pieces fit together.  In my head I had expected the spar to be just one or two long pieces of beefy metal.  Not so.  There’s got to be thirty pieces or so.  Once assembled they essentially form one long beefy chunk of metal, but with intricacies.

I emailed Kerry and asked for pictures to help be understand.  He sent me some, but what really helped what a blog from a guy I know as Onex Mike.  This spelled it out for me with just the right pictures.  Thank Mike!

Onces that was figured out, I had to drill holes in all the ribs, beams, supports and other stuff.  I finally finished today.  The shear quantity of material in this spar multiplies the work.  I’ll sheepishly admit that I thought I’d be done with the spar in a day or so.  Oh well.  One step after another. The picture below is the clecoed spar ready to updrill.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hundreds of Holes</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/08/hundreds-of-holes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hundreds of Holes" /><published>2017-05-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/08/hundreds-of-holes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/08/hundreds-of-holes.html">&lt;p&gt;Friday was a busy day and I only got to work 4 hours fabricating parts for the main spar.  This morning I fabricated about 8 more parts.  Then the main spar webs.  These are 2 long, heavy pieces of aluminum that provide the main structure of the main spar.  They came prefabricated to the right shape with pilot holes, but the pilot holes are tiny, not even a pin hole.  But thank goodness they are there.  It would take a very long time to measure those 100’s of locations.  And without a pilot hole, there’s always minor errors in where the drill actually penetrates the metal and they can add up.  With the pilot hole, small though it may be, the drill bit tends to seek it out and follow it through making precisely located holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took hours to drill all those holes.  Note there are two layers in the picture, the bottom layer as more holes than the top.   I got a work out wrestling those parts to hold still in the right place on the drill press, 100’s of times. Then it took hours to debur.  I also filed the edges to remove stress risers.  Tedious work.  Now they are ready to mate with the the other spar parts and I’ll get to up-drill all the holes and debur them again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-08/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Main Spar Webs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Friday was a busy day and I only got to work 4 hours fabricating parts for the main spar.  This morning I fabricated about 8 more parts.  Then the main spar webs.  These are 2 long, heavy pieces of aluminum that provide the main structure of the main spar.  They came prefabricated to the right shape with pilot holes, but the pilot holes are tiny, not even a pin hole.  But thank goodness they are there.  It would take a very long time to measure those 100’s of locations.  And without a pilot hole, there’s always minor errors in where the drill actually penetrates the metal and they can add up.  With the pilot hole, small though it may be, the drill bit tends to seek it out and follow it through making precisely located holes.

It took hours to drill all those holes.  Note there are two layers in the picture, the bottom layer as more holes than the top.   I got a work out wrestling those parts to hold still in the right place on the drill press, 100’s of times. Then it took hours to debur.  I also filed the edges to remove stress risers.  Tedious work.  Now they are ready to mate with the the other spar parts and I’ll get to up-drill all the holes and debur them again!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What a Mess</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/04/what-a-mess.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What a Mess" /><published>2017-05-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/04/what-a-mess</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/04/what-a-mess.html">&lt;p&gt;Three hours after beginning work I had everything cleaned up.  The fiberglass mold I laid out yesterday came off the plane very nicely.  The plane is not glued together in terrible ways… whew!  But boy was it a mess.  Wax, silicon film, clay, and epoxy all over the place.  These are not the type of products where a dry paper towel simply soaks up the mess.  I has to use a putty knife, mineral spirits, alcohol, scotch-brite, and dozens of paper towels. To make matters worse, I found dried epoxy finger prints on portions of the plane I didn’t protect with mold release agents (2nd pic).  I was wearing gloves and must not have noticed that I spilled some epoxy on my fingers.  It took a good portion of elbow grease to get those out.  The good news is that epoxy sticks to aluminum very well which means I can use some micro putty to create smaller permanent fairings on other joints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was all worth it.  After lots cutting the fairing piece and lots of sanding, it’s done.  See the first picture.  I love this solution far more than kit solution. Let me count the ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 piece instead of two&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8 screws instead of 20&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I installed a nut plate for each screw wherease the kit used sheet metal screws that thread into the sheet metal!?  They even warn you in the plans not to over tighten the screws less they strip.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All 3 joints have a fairing to improve aerodynamics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About 40 rivets are covered up, reducing drag.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better lines and no gaps between parts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cons? Well, a polished aluminum finish here won’t work… not that this matters for me, and there are already a bunch of fiberglass parts (like wing tips).  The weight is about the same as the aluminum covers.  My biggest concern is that it’s untested.  I think it’ll work great but I’m not sure how it’ll hold up to 150 knot winds.  Worst case scenario is that the wind rips it off and the plane will experience more drag.  Not a deal breaker.  I’m considering adding more glass to reinforce the part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued work on the wing bellcrank mounts that I started yesterday, but the plans are ambiguous.  It’s unclear exactly how some peices are supposed to be assembled.  Measurements are missing.  So rather then drill holes and pull rivets in the wrong place, I’m putting this task on hold until I know exactly how the parts are supposed to fit with the rest of the wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That brings me to the main spar.  The last picture shows the majority of material required.  I still have a few beams to cut.  This is going to be a hefty meld of metal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-04/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finished Fairing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-04/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finger Prints&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-04/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Main Spar Material&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Three hours after beginning work I had everything cleaned up.  The fiberglass mold I laid out yesterday came off the plane very nicely.  The plane is not glued together in terrible ways… whew!  But boy was it a mess.  Wax, silicon film, clay, and epoxy all over the place.  These are not the type of products where a dry paper towel simply soaks up the mess.  I has to use a putty knife, mineral spirits, alcohol, scotch-brite, and dozens of paper towels. To make matters worse, I found dried epoxy finger prints on portions of the plane I didn’t protect with mold release agents (2nd pic).  I was wearing gloves and must not have noticed that I spilled some epoxy on my fingers.  It took a good portion of elbow grease to get those out.  The good news is that epoxy sticks to aluminum very well which means I can use some micro putty to create smaller permanent fairings on other joints.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tail Fairing</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/03/tail-fairing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tail Fairing" /><published>2017-05-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/03/tail-fairing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/03/tail-fairing.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m not at all pleased with the way the tail panels came out.  See the first picture.  They required lots of bending to make them fit. It was non-trivial and I think I did a poor job.  This became an opportunity to try out some composite technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First was the play-dough, err modelling clay.  You can see a rough fill of the corners.  I left the panels in to give a shape to work around but they’ll go when it’s done.  Then I smoothed out the clay and removed the excess.  I’ve never sculpted much so this took a couple hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I was using the body of the plane as a mold, I had to take precautions to make sure the epoxy doesn’t stick to the plane.  This fairing will be removable so there’s access to the tail section.  I feared the epoxy would go everywhere and glue the plane in terrible ways.  So I took double precautions.  Mirror Wax, and Silicon spray. Both are mold release agents.  I really hope they do the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cut the fiberglass and peel pry.  Weighed it, and started mixing the epoxy.  Layer by layer I laid out the material and wetted it.  The glass is quite capable of handing the curves but the peel pry, not so much.  If I had to do it again, I’d cut small pieces to better fit the mold.  This was using one piece per layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While that sets, I bolted the engine mount and fabricated some parts for the wing fold assembly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-03/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Panels&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-03/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rough Clay&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-03/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Smooth Clay&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-03/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fiber&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-03/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Engine Mount&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">I’m not at all pleased with the way the tail panels came out.  See the first picture.  They required lots of bending to make them fit. It was non-trivial and I think I did a poor job.  This became an opportunity to try out some composite technique.

First was the play-dough, err modelling clay.  You can see a rough fill of the corners.  I left the panels in to give a shape to work around but they’ll go when it’s done.  Then I smoothed out the clay and removed the excess.  I’ve never sculpted much so this took a couple hours.

Since I was using the body of the plane as a mold, I had to take precautions to make sure the epoxy doesn’t stick to the plane.  This fairing will be removable so there’s access to the tail section.  I feared the epoxy would go everywhere and glue the plane in terrible ways.  So I took double precautions.  Mirror Wax, and Silicon spray. Both are mold release agents.  I really hope they do the job.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tail Gear</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/02/tail-gear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tail Gear" /><published>2017-05-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/02/tail-gear</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/02/tail-gear.html">&lt;p&gt;File!  Grind!  File!  That’s how the day began.  The horizontal tail and the rudder need to travel 25° up and down, left and right respectively.  Not only that, their lever arms need to hit squarely with the surfaces they meet at the end of their travel.  To achieve this meant lots of grinding with the dremel and filing with the files.  To my delight, I achieved the required travel on each surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon I made a trip to Ace, my home away from home it seems.  I needed the tiniest drill bit for the hinge cotter pins, and the biggest drill bit for the tail gear spring, which they didn’t have.  For the tail gear spring (a 2 foot long steel bar 5/8” in diameter) hole I drilled up the my biggest bit 1/2”.  Of course the spring didn’t fit.  I dremeled for a while and filed for a while trying to widen the hole without much success.  So I got creative and wrapped some emery paper (sand paper tape) around a drill bit, wedged it into the hole and spun the drill.  This was impressive.  Aluminum dust clouds sprung out from the hole and it made a nice smooth finish whereas the filing and dremeling looked sloppy. After adding a bit more tape a few times, the hole was the perfect size!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, I slid the spring through the hole and up to the mount in the rear of the tail.  It didn’t fit.  Of course I made several attempts to get it in but it was WAY too tight in the back of the tail.  I sighed, and drilled our a couple dozen rivets on the right skin to open up the area.  This worked.  But the mounts were installed too close together and the spring wouldn’t fit between them.  So I drilled those rivets and re-fabricated the mounts.  Even with the open skin it was very challenging to attach the spring bar.  To any future OneX builders, consider leaving the tail portion of one skin un-riveted, tempting though it may be to close it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried on the tail wheel. The push rod, used to steer the tail gear, was too short.  I figured I could cut 1/2 off the spring to make it reach.  Out came the grinding wheel and fireworks ensued.  It’s impressive how many sparks fly when you cut steel.  And that smell… mmmm… 4th of July!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then a 1/4” hole had to be drilled in to the tail wheel assembly and spring to hold them together.  Here’s what I learned:  Drill bits can tolerate aluminum.  But steel is the bane of drill bits.  It scars them rendering the poor bits dull and useless.  You know this happens when the bits just spins, smoke comes out of the hole, and everything becomes scolding hot.  You can’t just drill a 1/4” hole ya know.  You have to start small, drilling the hole with incrementally bigger bits.  I’m gonna have to go back to Ace soon and buy a new set of bits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tiny cotter pins go into each end of the hinges to lock the interior hinge rod in place.  The bit was so small it didn’t fit in my drill.  I had to wrap it with masking tape to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-02/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Opened Tail&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-02/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Gear&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-02/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hinge Ping&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">File!  Grind!  File!  That’s how the day began.  The horizontal tail and the rudder need to travel 25° up and down, left and right respectively.  Not only that, their lever arms need to hit squarely with the surfaces they meet at the end of their travel.  To achieve this meant lots of grinding with the dremel and filing with the files.  To my delight, I achieved the required travel on each surface.

In the afternoon I made a trip to Ace, my home away from home it seems.  I needed the tiniest drill bit for the hinge cotter pins, and the biggest drill bit for the tail gear spring, which they didn’t have.  For the tail gear spring (a 2 foot long steel bar 5/8” in diameter) hole I drilled up the my biggest bit 1/2”.  Of course the spring didn’t fit.  I dremeled for a while and filed for a while trying to widen the hole without much success.  So I got creative and wrapped some emery paper (sand paper tape) around a drill bit, wedged it into the hole and spun the drill.  This was impressive.  Aluminum dust clouds sprung out from the hole and it made a nice smooth finish whereas the filing and dremeling looked sloppy. After adding a bit more tape a few times, the hole was the perfect size!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tight Quarters</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/01/tight-quarters.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tight Quarters" /><published>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/01/tight-quarters</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/01/tight-quarters.html">&lt;p&gt;The tail is attached!  It all began last Friday.  Christoph, a colleague from 8th Light in London was in town for a conference.  After we flew to Sedona for lunch I convinced him to help me attach the tail surfaces to the fuselage.  We tried out the vertical tail and with a little finagling, got the gist of it figured out, though we didn’t fasten anything yet.  Then we tried on the horizontal tail and this is where it hit the fan.  It wasn’t fitting, at all.  The bottom skin was too long.  Then Christoph asked “Is it possible that the skin is up side down?”  Fear overtook me.  I checked the plans, made some measurements, and realized the truth. I had installed it upside down!  How could it be?  I checked them several times before installing and even wrote on the skins in sharpie to identify which way was up and which was was down.  Some how I got them backwards.  The horror!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this such a big deal?  The skin is held on with around 250 rivets.  Reversing it means drilling out all the rivits, flipping the skins and installing 250 new rivets.  As we’ve learned, rivets don’t always come out nicely.  If I could drill 9 out of 10 rivets successfully, which would be pretty good, that’d leave 25 wrecked rivet holes, not to mention hours of effort. The upside is that reversing the skins is possible because other than the slight difference in length where they meet the fuselage, that are symmetrical top to bottom. But I felt like crying.  Christoph and I called it a day and got some beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day I drove out to Deer Valley airport to fly with Denny (other OneX builder) in his RV-12.  He did a great job building that plane and we had a very nice flight.  But the point is that on the drive there and back I figured out a solution to my horizontal tail skins.  First, I could cut the bottom side (which was supposed to the top) to fit.  This would leave a 1/2 inch gap on the top.  But I had already considered crafting some fairings.  We learned a technique to make fairings out of composite materials (fiberglass) in the EAA workshops I went to in Las Vegas.  Not only would this cover the gap, but it would also make the plane more aerodynamic!  Double win!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I cut the skins to size.  Christoph helped me file it down, then file it some more, and again until it fit perfectly.  It turns out that had I installed the skins properly we would have had to file away a good bit of material anyway.  In the end, there was only a minor gap on the front top side, maybe 1/4 inch.  This was all very relieving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I continued fastening the tail surfaces, and I’m just about done.  That tail section is tight!  It has been very challenging to get the nuts on and tightened because nothing is directly accessible.  I was constantly reaching through inspection holes and between parts, and half the time my socket wrench was useless because it wouldn’t fit.  I had to go buy second set of wrenches to get it done.  And Luka had to come and help me reach parts that were impossible for me and my fat hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still work to be done here but I think the worst parts are done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-01/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Christoph With Tail&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-01/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Attached&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">The tail is attached!  It all began last Friday.  Christoph, a colleague from 8th Light in London was in town for a conference.  After we flew to Sedona for lunch I convinced him to help me attach the tail surfaces to the fuselage.  We tried out the vertical tail and with a little finagling, got the gist of it figured out, though we didn’t fasten anything yet.  Then we tried on the horizontal tail and this is where it hit the fan.  It wasn’t fitting, at all.  The bottom skin was too long.  Then Christoph asked “Is it possible that the skin is up side down?”  Fear overtook me.  I checked the plans, made some measurements, and realized the truth. I had installed it upside down!  How could it be?  I checked them several times before installing and even wrote on the skins in sharpie to identify which way was up and which was was down.  Some how I got them backwards.  The horror!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dimple Debacle</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/27/dimple-debacle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dimple Debacle" /><published>2017-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/27/dimple-debacle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/27/dimple-debacle.html">&lt;p&gt;Three trips to the hardware store today.  The first was to Ace to get a thread tap to make a threaded hole in the bellcrannk faces.  Those are done. They’re for translating control inputs from the inside part of the wing to the outside, and they’re pretty nifty.  Remeber the wings fold up.  There’s a outboard set of paddles and an inbourd set of paddles.  They lines up with eachother on a swivel.  When one rotates, it pushes the other making it rotate.  See the first pic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debacle.  Sonex includes two Super Simple Dimple Dies in the kit to dimple surfaces for flush rivets.  There’a big one for 1/8” holes and small one for 3/32” holes.  Basically they are two plates of hard metal. When you squeeze them together tightly with the sheet metal in the middle, they bend a little dimple in the sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each set comes with two nails that go through the center so that you can pull them together with a rivet puller.  The small set has skinny nails, understandably.  The first one broke on the first hole I dimpled.  It’s a lot of force required to bend the metal.  The second got me 6 more dimples and broke on the 7th. But it allowed me to finish the wheel pants connectors.  Today I had to dimple the tail mount to install some bolt plates, but I was out of skinny nails; specifically 4D-2” nails.  Earlier in the week I checked at the local Ace and they didn’t have any.  This moring I called Fountain Hill’s Ace and they told me they had two boxes in stock.  So I went over there (2nd trip of the day), but they didn’t have them.  The guys at the store concluded that their manufactureer just didn’t make 4D-2” nails, at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found some music wire that was the right diameter and is really strong, figuring we could bend a head on one end and cut it to length.  I got home and tried it out, several times.  It didn’t work.  The wire, strong as it was, would bend, or snap at the point where I bent a head on it.  My 3rd trip was to Home Depot to see if they had the 4D-2” nails.  They didn’t.  I bought a high temp map blow torch insted.  This allowed me to play blacksmith, hammering the hot wire against my vice making very creative bends.  They all snapped off.  Then I tried the simplest thing.  With red hot wire tip, I just smashed it flat. That worked.  &lt;em&gt;whew&lt;/em&gt;!  You can see all the attempts and the dimple dies in the second pic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third pic is the application of the dimples to attach those nut plates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-27/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bellcranks&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-27/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nail Fails&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-27/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Mount&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Three trips to the hardware store today.  The first was to Ace to get a thread tap to make a threaded hole in the bellcrannk faces.  Those are done. They’re for translating control inputs from the inside part of the wing to the outside, and they’re pretty nifty.  Remeber the wings fold up.  There’s a outboard set of paddles and an inbourd set of paddles.  They lines up with eachother on a swivel.  When one rotates, it pushes the other making it rotate.  See the first pic.</summary></entry></feed>
