<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://micahmartin.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-08-15T20:39:20-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com//</id><title type="html">OneX Build Log</title><subtitle>I'm building an airplane.  This is how it went so far.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">First Flights</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2018/01/29/first-flights.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Flights" /><published>2018-01-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-01-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2018/01/29/first-flights</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2018/01/29/first-flights.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a compilation video of the first two test flight days.  More detail is provided in the blog below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/254629471&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jan-24-2018---preparation&quot;&gt;Jan 24, 2018 - Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the airworthiness certificate in hand, there was no reason to wait.  I asked Denny Myrick and Dennis Smith, both Sonex builders, if they’d be willing to help and support me for the first flight.  They were happy to be a part of it and I’m glad they came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scottsdale Airport tower was very accommodating.  I had called then on the phone a couple times to let then know I’d be test flying my experimental aircraft.  They suggested early morning on days when there’s no big events in town, to avoid all the jet traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had prepared flight cards and a test plan for the day, so we started by reviewing that.  One element I had in the plan was to make the first flight a few feet off the ground, then land right away.  Denny and Dennis strongly advised against this.  I heeded their advise.  But they did agree that a couple high speed taxis were a good start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2018-01-29/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Denny and Dennis&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;high-speed-taxi&quot;&gt;High Speed Taxi&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;steering&quot;&gt;Steering&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxing the airplane for the first time once I got it to Scottsdale Airport was a lot of fun.  I taxied it to the self-serve fuel tank and filled her up, took a couple rides around that hangars… It’s easy to steer and get around smoothly.  But I had never gone more than 10-15mph.  When I started moving down the runway approaching 55mph, it was a whole new game.  The plane became very squirrelly, zig-zagging left and right.  I felt like was tap dancing with my toes on the rudder pedals.  From the sidelines, my support team did not observe any swerving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;burbling-engine&quot;&gt;Burbling Engine&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right as I got to full throttle, the engine burbled… maybe thinking twice about whether it wanted to really wanted to provide that much power.  But only for a moment.  Then it growled nicely.  This was one hint that the mixture setting in the AeroInjectors was not calibrated well.  There were more hints later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;left-rudder&quot;&gt;Left Rudder&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a student pilot, you hear it over and over:  “More right rudder”.  It becomes muscle memory; your throttle hand is connected to your right foot.  When you add power you add right rudder to compensate for torque and p-factor pulling to the left.  The Volkswagen in my OneX spins counter-clockwise, opposite certified plane engines.  It pulls to the right which means I have to compensate with left rudder.  That added to my swerving problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;lifting-the-tail&quot;&gt;Lifting the Tail&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After accelerating upto 50mph, I pushed on the stick to get the tail off the ground.  And I pushed hard!  The tail reluctantly hopped off the ground, at which point I released pressure and it fell back down.  I tried a couple more times to lift the tail while I continued rolling down the runway… It really didn’t want to leave the ground.  The solution was obvious to Denny and Dennis when I told them.  “Oh, just trim your elevators down.”  Doh!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;brakes&quot;&gt;Brakes&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7000’ down the runway I passed the 1000’ stripes at the opposite end, still at 50mph.  There was plenty of room to stop so I keeped power in and practiced more.  Consider, I had upgraded to hydraulic brake, and in my shop they worked great.  I could set the brakes and it was like the tires were bolted to the floor.  And stopping from a 10mph taxi was a piece of cake.  But at that point in my high speed taxi run I had to just a few hundred feet to decelerate from 50mph, or else find myself in thick gravel at the end of the runway. As I applied the brakes, they felt different… not as much deceleration as I was expecting.  I pulled harder to little effect.  The plane was slowing, but now enough.  The taxi line for the last exit passes behind me and runway-end lights were right in front of me.  As a last resort I started pumping the brakes, they got tighter, and I stopped within a few feet of the light posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2018-01-29/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Getting Ready&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;engine-check&quot;&gt;Engine Check&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After two high speed taxi runs, I met my crew back at the hangar.  We remove the cowling and checked for problems.  There was a tiny bit of oil leaking from one of the valve covers so we tightened the bolts.  Other that that, everything looked great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We debriefed and discussed the high speed taxis.  Denny and Dennis had plenty of experience to share and advise to offer.  After 30 minutes or so, we gat back to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denny grabbed the hand-held radio to listen in on the tower frequency and communicate with me if needed.  I hopped back into the plane, did one more high speed taxi, just to get a better feel for it.  Then it was go time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;first-flight&quot;&gt;First Flight&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to confess, I was a bit terrified.  Could these scraps of metal I put together really fly?  And more importantly, land safely?  My breathing was heavy and I could feel my heart beating as I waited for clearance to take off.  As soon as I got the clearance, a calmness overtook me and stayed with me until I got back to the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;take-off&quot;&gt;Take Off&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be frank, the take off was unremarkable.  Just like any other plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With only 80hp, the OneX climbs at about 600-800 feet per minute.  I’m used to climbing out of Scottsdale at about 1,500 - 2,000 fpm, or more when piloting charter flights in the jet.  But that’s okay.  600 fpm was a relaxing climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2018-01-29/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First Take Off&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;handling&quot;&gt;Handling&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as it was squirrelly on the ground, so was it in the air.  I could feel every little bump, eddie, and current in the air.  But at the same time, this OneX was super nimble.  The slightest touch on the controls and the bird was more than eager to respond.  Fun as that may sound, this was the first flight and only the gentlest of maneuvers was called for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;egts&quot;&gt;EGTs&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climbing to 3,000’ (500’ above the pattern), I banked to the left and I banked to the right.  Reaching 3,000’ I noticed the EGTs (exhaust gas temperatures) were in the red.  I wrote down the temps and reduced power.  With less power I lost altitude and the tower didn’t like me so close to pattern altitude.  They told me so over the radio. So I added power back in and the temps went into the red again.  I continued the flight, keeping an eye on the temps and being shy with the throttle.   This was the other clue that the mixture was too lean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;flaps&quot;&gt;Flaps&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denny and Dennis warned me that the flaps might be hard to deploy.  They weren’t kidding.  At 100mph, I did not have the strength in one arm to pull back the lever all the way to the detent.  At 80mph, I could pull the flaps lever back, but I could not get it to stay in the detent.  This revealed a flaw in my fabrication.  The lever should have a bias toward going into the detent, but my lever required a little twist that was impossible to apply at speed.  So I stopped using the flaps for this flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;winds&quot;&gt;Winds&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While dawdling around in the air, I thought I heard Denny’s voice on the radio saying something about a runway change.  The tower asked “Experimental 321NX, was that you?”.  Confused I responded “Negative.”  A few minutes later I heard Denny on the radio talking directly to me: “Micah, wait for the runway change.  Land on 3.”  Hmmm….  As an aside, the tower did not like that.  They called operations, and operations hunted down Denny to chew him out.  But why would Denny tell me that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I took off, winds were calm.  Denny’s call came in maybe 25 minutes later.  I started to pay more attention to the radio.  Tower was reporting winds out of 090 at 12 knots gusting to 20!  Scottsdale has runways 3/21, meaning that’s serious cross wind; certainly more than I wanted for my test flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;go-arounds&quot;&gt;Go Arounds&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the runway switch was initiated, I was done with my test plan and requested a landing.  They put me first in line for runway 3.  Everything felt great until I lined up on final and felt like crab, moving sideways through the air.  The crosswinds were not going to make this landing easy.  I fumbled with the controls trying to compensate for the wind, but I was not used to such a nimble and sensitive plane.  “Experimental 321WA going around.” I said over the radio as I anxiously applied full throttle. The engine roared to life, thank goodness, and I climbed back up to pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tower put me behind a Cirrus for the next landing.  Maybe I jumped the gun on my turn to final, or the Cirrus just enjoyed a long leisurely roll down the runway.  We were too close.  Tower:  “Experimental 321NX, go around, traffic.”  Doh!  The engine roared to life again, thank goodness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Third time I was following a Cessna and there was plenty of separation.  This was it.  I had to get on the ground, wind or not.  Again I twisted and turned on final trying to compensate for the wind.  By short final I was relatively stable, but then a nice big gust came right as I was flaring.  When I touched down, my right wing was picked up by the wind nearly forcing my left to touch the ground.  I wrestled the plane back down and rolled safely to my exit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;success&quot;&gt;Success&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment I exited the runway and came to a stop, I was overcome with a wave of adrenaline.  My heart was beating out of my chest and lungs stretching full with air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I taxied back to the hangar, a band of pilots and builders had organically gathered to welcome me.  Word of a first test flight gets around it seems.  Congratulatory handshakes capped off the momentous occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put the plane away, drove home, and slept the rest of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;second-flight&quot;&gt;Second Flight&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flap lever adjusted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AeroInjector needed calibrated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oil Changed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engine and airframe inspected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I performed the above maintenance and a couple days later it was time for my second test flight.  This one turned out to be quite exciting.  Words wont do it justice though.  You really aught to watch the video to see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moral: Be weary of that AeroInjector jam nut.  Make sure it’s really tight, even at the expense of moving the fuel needle a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2018-01-29/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Soaring&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Video</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Red Tape</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2018/01/23/red-tape.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Red Tape" /><published>2018-01-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-01-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2018/01/23/red-tape</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2018/01/23/red-tape.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;registration&quot;&gt;Registration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Registration finally arrived in the mail on Jan 17th.  On the same day, I filled out all my airworthiness application paperwork and sent it to Ted (the DAR - Designated Airworthiness Representative).  He pointed out several errors; most notably my tail numbers.  According to the FARs, they must be horizontal (or vertical), not angles like mine.  Doh!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were stickers I purchased from Stiker Mule and there was no way they were coming off in one piece.  So rather than buy new stickers and wait for them to come, I decided to cut my own from left over vinyl.  And while I was at it, I could get creative.  So I found the Transformers fort and made some larger two-tone numbers that would blend right into my design.  The next day I installed them, proudly took a picture and sent to to Ted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He calls me that evening to tell me that the FAA does not approve.  He had show them to his contact and they did not like them.  The two-tone effect had to go, and the aspect ratio of the characters was incorrect.  Bah!  Vogons!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2018-01-23/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First Two Tail Numbers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This next version of tail numbers is approved by the FAA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2018-01-23/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Final Tail Numbers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;airworthiness-inspection&quot;&gt;Airworthiness Inspection&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the paperwork complete and corrected, Ted meets me yesterday to do the airworthiness inspection.  First thing he does is walk around the airplane looking for something. Then he asks me “Where’s your data plate?”  My shoulder drop as I sigh… “What’s a data plate?”  So you know, it’s a fireproof (steel) plate riveted to the side of the aircraft with data etched (engraved) into it: Make, Model, Serial Number.  Ted was kid enough to continue the inspection but was unable to issue an airworthiness certificate without seeing the data plate installed with the correct information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I raced around to get it done.  I got the steel cards from grumpy sheet metal machinist near the airport.  A local trophy shop engraved it for me.  Then I went back to the airport, riveted it in place and sent a picture to Ted.  He came back the next day and…. viola… I got my airworthiness certificate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2018-01-23/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Data Plate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Registration</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To the Airport</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2018/01/10/to-the-airport.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To the Airport" /><published>2018-01-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-01-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2018/01/10/to-the-airport</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2018/01/10/to-the-airport.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;tweaks&quot;&gt;Tweaks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My family has been laughing at me as I work on my completed plane.   Even though the build is complete, there’s still work to be done people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paperwork - The FAA sent back part of my registration application because of a silly mistake I made.  I fixed it and mailed it back last week.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trim elevator control holes - Denny Myrick came over to see the plane and noticed the elevator control rod rubbing against as bulkhead.  Fixed!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Luggage rack - Early on I bought Sonex’s luggage “bag”.  But it was just a bag with nothing to attach it in place.  So I build a rack, sewed some velcro, and bam!… Luggage rack complete.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Placards - Regulations require a few placards and I added a few more:  baggage capacity, fuel, “EXPERIMENTAL”, fire extinguisher, elt, flaps, brakes, etc…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seal for windshield - There was a gap so I added some foam tape to seal it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Polish engine caps - Thay had become all scuffed up during the work.  Time to make them shine!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;insurance&quot;&gt;Insurance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first place I called was, lets call it “Acme”, because they were listed on Sonex’s website.  They told me I need 10 hours of duel time in make and model, with an instructor.  I told the lady my plane’s make and model has only 1 seat.  She said “I know.  That’s a problem.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately I know an underwriter, Jim, at Starr Aviation.  He recommended a couple brokers, who then asked Jim to quote my policy.  In the end I went with Falcon Insurance, underwritten by Starr.  Now I’m insured for half the price of Acme’s quote, with no dual time required.  Yay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tow-truck&quot;&gt;Tow Truck&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting the plane to the airport is a problem I’d been pondering for a while.  With insurance bound, there was no reason to wait.  I called Scottdale Towing Co. because they were the closest.  They sent me a flat bed truck with a driver named Edmundo an hour later.  Edmundo was awesome!  He patiently helped me get the plane on the truck bed and carefully fasten it securely.  He allowed me to choose the attach points and asked me to check his tension on each strap to make sure it wasn’t too tight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked that we stay under 35mph on the way to the airport and he was fine with that.  In fact he rarely went above 30mph.  Edmundo took every turn very slowly and dodged a dozen trees from hitting those high wings.   Unlike stories from other builders who say their plane bounced all over the truck bed, mine stuck like it was bolted down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boy did we get a lot of looks from neighbors, pedestrians, and other drivers.  It’s not every day you see a plane driving down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrived at the airport and the plane was in pristine condition.  Not a scratch.  Edmundo gently lowered it and helped me put it in the hangar.  It shares the new home with the Cirrus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2018-01-10/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;At Home&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2018-01-10/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Truck&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2018-01-10/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;At Airport&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2018-01-10/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;In Hangar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Tweaks</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Build Completed</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/21/build-completed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Build Completed" /><published>2017-12-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-12-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/21/build-completed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/21/build-completed.html">&lt;p&gt;The Onex is Done!  Time for champagne!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a quick walkaround of the finished plane:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/248395316&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;weighing&quot;&gt;Weighing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A required step in applying for airworthiness is calculating weight and balance.  Fellow EAA chapter 538 member, Chris Rute, has some precise scales ment for race cars.  He was kind enough to bring them over and help me out.  Each wheel goes on a separate scale and the main display shows you the weights.  It’s was so sensitive that slight breezes would change the numbers.  Results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Right Main Gear: 294 lbs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Left Main Gear: 294 lbs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tail Wheel: 30 lbs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Total Weight: 618 lbs - just 18 lbs more than the plans claim.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-21/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chris Rute&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nose-cowling&quot;&gt;Nose Cowling&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick’s design called for the top to be solid green.  But the compound curves around the nose made is soooo difficult.  There’s too much extra material around the bends that the vinyl wrinkles and it’s impossible to get it flat, at least for me.  It’s like trying to wrap paper around a ball.  After 4 attempts I gave up.  Angelique suggested I strategically add some stripes.  I played with her idea trying to follow the curves that were already in the design.  What I ended up with is a “swoosh” where the black comes around the front and back along the top.  Angelique, who is usually very critical of my work, says it’s perfect…. that it “makes the plane”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;decepticon-logo&quot;&gt;Decepticon Logo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My sister Angela would see planes fly low over her house and ask me, “Was that you?”  Of course I’ve flown over her house before, but not all sightings were me.  She told me that I should put a big Transformers logo on the bottom of my plane so that she’d know it was me.  You see, when I was a child, Transformers were my toy of choice, for years!  I love the idea of having a transformers plane.  So for this plane I did what she suggested.  And loyal to the original 1980’s Transformers, planes are Decepticons.  I was always a fan of the Constructacon’s green color scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Decepticon logos took hours to make.  I printed out an image, drew a grid on the paper, and translated the points onto a 2’x2’ piece of purple vinyl.  Fortunately the logo is all straight lines!  The purple was hard to see against the black, so I added a green boarder to make it pop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I think the Decepticon logos add at least 5 points on the cool factor.  I have my own, real life, Transformer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stickers&quot;&gt;Stickers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A while back I reserved my tail number: N321NX, for my OneX.  Get it?  Anyway, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stickermule.com/products/vinyl-lettering&quot;&gt;Sticker Mule&lt;/a&gt; had sent me a email about their new vinyl lettering service.  I figure it could save me some time cutting letters so I bought my tail numbers.  And I also got a “Capt. Micah D Martin” sticker for the cockpit just like they do on milatary aircraft.  Technically I am a captain, an air charter captain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-21/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Left Rear&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-21/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Front&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-21/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Right, Wing Up&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-21/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Boys&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had hoped to have my airworthiness certificate in hand before the end of the year.  Not so.  The DAR (FAA representative who inspects experimental aircraft for airworthiness) informed me that I have to fill out forms and applications that the FAA must review first.  I’ll submit the forms this week, but since I leave for France this weekend, the inspection will have to wait for next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a GoPro so I can film my first flights and I will post videos on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">The Onex is Done!  Time for champagne!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Xmas Wrapping</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/13/xmas-wrapping.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Xmas Wrapping" /><published>2017-12-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-12-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/13/xmas-wrapping</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/13/xmas-wrapping.html">&lt;p&gt;No, not wrapping presents yet.  Vinyl wrapping is has been this weeks activity.  But first…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;charter-flight&quot;&gt;Charter Flight&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I piloted another charter flight last Thursday.  KSDL (Sottsdale) -&amp;gt; KLAX (Los Angeles) -&amp;gt; KLAS (Las Vegas) -&amp;gt; KSGU (St. George, UT) -&amp;gt; KSDL.  Long day, great for flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sedona-hike&quot;&gt;Sedona Hike&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, Rob and Hannah Mooi flew up to Sedona with Angelique and I.  We had a delightful breakfast and scenic hike.  Awesome day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-13/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hike&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wrapping&quot;&gt;Wrapping&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outboard wings are quite long.  You can see in the first pic below the one skeet of grey wrap for the underside of the wing.  It’s all wrinkly at first, but looks really nice when “glassed” into place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-13/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Loose Wrap&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday I was able to get the tops of the right wing and both horizontal tail surfaces.  The right side of the design has these simple stripes that I think add a nice bit of character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lesson Learned&lt;/em&gt; - So… looking the wrapped wing, within 10”, you can see where I applied the micro-balloons.  It’s like, everywhere is glassy smooth, then a patch of mud, then more smooth surface.  When I had sanded down my patches, the surfaces looked silky smooth with an edgeless transition between the silver aluminum and white micro-paste.  Maybe the white color was the problem.  Once the vinyl when down, the edge of the patches became obvious and you can even see the grain of my sanding.  Every imperfection is pronounced.  &lt;em&gt;sigh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-13/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Right Side Wrapped&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Cherry Max rivets arrived Monday night, I was able to close up the wings on Tuesday.  Then I added more micro-paste to the new rivets lines, for consistency.  However, I used it sparingly this time. When dry, I applied full force sanding effort even pulling out the power tools… well just my oscillating tool with the sanding attachment.  Starting with a course grit, I sanded, then repeated with finner grit paper, then even finer.  Dust everywhere!  But, this time is was really smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With both wings fully wrapped, the most recent surfaces look much better then the original.  But there are still visibile imperfections that I didn’t notice before wrapping.  Clearly I need to improves my body work skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-13/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wings Wrapped&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also an attempt to wrap the top of the nose cowling.  But I eventually had to throw the whole sheet of vinyl away because it was over-worked, losing it’s adhesive.  Those compound curves!  After watching some vinyul wrap YouTube videos, I’ll try again by heating the vinyl first and start by stretching it around the curviest part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I also ran of our vinyl today and had to order more.  Fortunately I have plenty of scraps and smaller surfaces to wrap in the mean time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">No, not wrapping presents yet.  Vinyl wrapping is has been this weeks activity.  But first…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">End in Sight</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/06/end-in-sight.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="End in Sight" /><published>2017-12-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-12-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/06/end-in-sight</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/06/end-in-sight.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;mel-achievement-unlocked&quot;&gt;MEL Achievement Unlocked&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday and Friday last week I completed my multi-engine training and passed the checkride.  I’m now multi-engine certified.  This is mostly so I can start training for second in command in Elite Flights Jets’ Eclipse Jet for charter flights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;exhaust-wrapping&quot;&gt;Exhaust Wrapping&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple builders suggested insulating the exhaust to protect the inside of the engine compartment from high heat.  This fiberglass wrapping kit took months to arrive from Aircraft Spruce, but it finally arrived and the wrapping process was fairly painless, and quite messy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wrapped Exhaust&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fairing-wrapping&quot;&gt;Fairing Wrapping&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the small fairings are wrapped.  Those counter weight fairings were just too curvy for one piece of vinyl.  All the otheres are seamless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wrapped Fairings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-preparation&quot;&gt;Wing Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added some more micro-balloons to the wings because I noticed some spots I missed and incomplete transition from my last application.  The next day I sanded, and sanded some more.  The boys gave me some weird looks because I was covered in dust.  And my arm was SORE. Remember Karate Kid? Sand the Wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sanded Wing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bottom-tail-skin&quot;&gt;Bottom Tail Skin&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While waiting for the epoxy to dry, I started to work on the bottom tail skin.  This is essentially the last part to attach, because once on, the tail is virtually inaccessible.  However, I saw on AirWard that there was a kit to make to the tail accessible by using nut plates.  Although I didn’t buy the kit, I had enough nut plates to make the rear half unattached, around 50.  That leaves about 70 rivets for the remainder of the skin. Using nut plated for all the holes, to make a fully removable skin, was not workable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While installing nutplates, I observed that the rear two bulkheads could benefit from some bolts.  I don’t think rivets or nutplates would do these bulkheads justice.  So I installed the bolts and was content with a more secured frame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skin is all ready for rivets and screws… but I’ll wait a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tail-fairing&quot;&gt;Tail Fairing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attempted to wrap the tail fairing unsuccessfully.  The vinyl just doen’t stick to the composite parts like it does to metal and plastic.  Especially back side where there’s a very thin layer of clay, from the mold, that I just can’t seem to remove sufficiently.  They vinyl just won’t hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I ripped it all off and threw it out.  Then I went to ace and bought some white enamel spray paint.  This should help the vinyl stick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Painted Fairing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wrapped-underside-of-wings&quot;&gt;Wrapped Underside of Wings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the wrapping begin!  I wrapped the underside of both inboard wings.  These are the first solid parts of the plane to be wrapped.  This is also a key step in closing up the wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with large sheets of vinyl, upside down is tricky.  And it was a windy morning which added to the fun.  There’s a couple small boo-boos on the right side which I did first.  The left turned out better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wrapped Underside&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-fold-disaster&quot;&gt;Wing Fold Disaster&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While working under the right wing, I heard a loud boom and the whole airplane started to shake and rock side to side.  It took a moment for me to realize that the wind had blown the left wing past the balance point and it fell open.  Ouch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wind opening the wings had been a nightmare of mine which is why I installed the wing locks as soon as the outboard wings were first attached.  At the time, the wing’s didn’t close cleanly. Parts would interfere and get caught on eachother.  On a few occasions I unknowingly bent skins, clecoes, and other parts when folding and unfolding wings.  The leverage on the wings is intense!  I repaired all the damage of course.  But the thought of wind blowing the wings open with no one to resist the force and detect problems… Disaster!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this part of the build, I am folding and unfolding the wings multiple time every day so the wing locks were not used.  Foolish me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incredibly, I could not find any damage.  Not one hint of it!  This is one tough plane.  Still, the thought of that single hinge bolt taking all the force of the falling wing in an instant… I decided to replace it.  Fortunately I had spare bolts.  Even more fortunately, in the midst of replacing the bolt I noticed that I had not yet installed the cotter pins for these bolts.  Good thing.  Installing the cotter pins would not have been possible once the wings were sealed and the cotter pins are rather critical.  If I had forgotten them and closed the wings, I would have stared at the left over pins scratching my head and probabaly never realizing where they were supposed to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bolt that took the hit was fine too… at least I could not detect any deformity.  Disaster turned into good fortune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-interior&quot;&gt;Wing Interior&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the vinyl was on, I was able to install the pitot/AOA probe, and the AOT probe for the final time.  I wired the AOT probe and connected the pitot/AOA plumbing.  Then I started the final installation of the flap control rods, completing only the left before I had to come in for dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Connected Pitot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">MEL Achievement Unlocked</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Waitng For Rivets</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/28/waitng-for-rivets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waitng For Rivets" /><published>2017-11-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/28/waitng-for-rivets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/28/waitng-for-rivets.html">&lt;p&gt;The wings are on hold while I wait for rivets.  So in the mean time…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pitotstaticaoa&quot;&gt;Pitot/Static/AOA&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dynon’s installation kit for the Pitot/Static/AOA is quite convenient.  They use fasteners  where you simply push the platic tubing in, and it’s sealed. At least I hope it is.  So I ran all the plumbing, from the static ports on the side and the pito/AOA tube on the right wing, to the ADAHRS unit.  The pitot tube will still be removed so I can wrap the bottom of the wing without making a seam, so it’s not fully connected yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pitot AOA Plumbing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The static ports are installed in roughly the same place they are on most other planes, the rear sides of the fuselage.  Flush rivets hole them in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Static Vents&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;air-vents&quot;&gt;Air Vents&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denny Myrick suggested these air vents from Vans.  I felt terrible cutting holes into the sife of the plane, but I think they turned out okay.  Now I can get some fresh air in the cockpit on those hot Arizona days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Air Vents&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;elt&quot;&gt;ELT&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A while back I decided to get an ELT (Emergency Location Transmitter) even though it’s not required on a single seat experimental aircraft.  This is the smalled ELT I could find wwighting in at only a couple pounds.  It has to be installed on the left side of the fuselage, with the antenna exposed throuth the canopy so locations where limited.  I fabricated a mount attached to the bottom left longeron that should hold it steady enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ELT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wheel-pants-skins&quot;&gt;Wheel Pants Skins&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve put these off for a while.  Now’s the time.  I cut them to fit and got them mounted. Then I took them off to wrap them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared the wrapping the ailerons, these wheel pant were much more difficult.  It’s the compound curves.  The vinyl has to stretch and compress to fit smoothy and sometimes it just can’t do it.  At first I tried to wrap them with one piece of each color.  Eventually I gave up used three pieces.  It still took a good deal of time and effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They look good…. from a distance.  Up close you’ll notice some white lines between pieces, crooked corners, and sealing tape around all the edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wheel Pants&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;aeroinjector&quot;&gt;Aeroinjector&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aeroinjector had to be repositioned to get the needed fuel flow.  I cur the 45° silicone tube I had ordered and got it into position.  Of course the cowling not longer fit because the air filter was protruding too much.  After a few attempts, I figured out that the aeroinjector intake could fit all the way into the airfilter, about 2”, and by adding some material to the perimeter of the intake nozzle, fasten the air filter.  Then the cowling fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aeroinjector is held on by a hose clamp and silicone tube.  The seems a bit precarious, so I used some adel clamps and aluminum strips to add extra braces.  Now it is fastened to the engine mount and won’t be going anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aeroinjector&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">The wings are on hold while I wait for rivets.  So in the mean time…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cherry Fairing Balloons</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/16/cherry-fairing-balloons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cherry Fairing Balloons" /><published>2017-11-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/16/cherry-fairing-balloons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/16/cherry-fairing-balloons.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;charter-flights&quot;&gt;Charter Flights&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I complete my first charter flight as a captain, taking a couple from Las Vegas to Page AZ.  Then I did two more flights this week.  It was fun, but left less time to work on the OneX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cherrymax-rivets&quot;&gt;CherryMax Rivets&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aircraftspruce.com/catalog/hapages/cherrymax4.php?gclid=EAIaIQobChMIl4OEvKbE1wIVkqDsCh03VgMLEAQYASABEgL5KvD_BwE&quot;&gt;CherryMax rivets&lt;/a&gt; arrived over the weekend. These bad boys look significantly more complex than normal rivets, and they work…. Awesome!  Maybe too awesome actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they are the perfect size.  Yes!  They fill the oversized holes and, Dang, do they hold on tight.  The binded surfaces seem very secure, and the shafts break off flush with the head.  How cool is that?!  No holes in the center of the rivet. There were a couple new rivets that I wanted to redo, and this is where they are a bit too awesome.  I could not drill it out.  Without the hole in the factory head, I couldn’t get my drill bit to hold still.  The material seem harder as well.  It must be the cadmium. So I tried to drill it from the back, but the shaft protrudes and again I can’t get any drill action.  So, the moral here is:  Don’t mess up a CherryMax rivet.  You won’t get it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tested all the flush rivets I had previously installed.  about 90% of them fell out with little convincing from my drill.  All but a few were replaced with the CherryMax rivets.  Then I continued to rivet the outboard panel with the new flush rivets, and I ran out.  Oops.  I mis calculated how many I needed.  No problem, I can order more…. except they are not on backorder and will be for weeks.  &lt;em&gt;-sad face-&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-16/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CherryMax Rivets&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;micro-paste&quot;&gt;Micro Paste&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the flush rivets installed, the front wing skins became a bit puckered.  Just slight warping of the skin around each rivet.  It didn’t look terrible, but the goal of the flush rivets is laminar flow.  The puckered skin won’t help, and I want to be able to show off smooth, flat wings once they’re wrapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I mixed up some micro paste, epoxy with micro balloons, that is comparable to bondo.  This I applied to a couple rivet lines, then I mixed some more micro paste, then some more. Fortunately this stuff is really light.  I’ve probably applied about 12oz, volumetrically, to smooth our rivets and seems between surfaces.  Maybe that’s like a 1/4 pound.  I’ve still got a bit more to add.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopfully, the sanding is not too laborious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-16/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Micro Paste&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fairings&quot;&gt;Fairings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the fairing, and mounting surfaces and been prepared with the nutplates.  From left to right we have: aileron counterweight, aileron pushrod, rudder cable,  and flap control rod.  These are just left side fairings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only flap control rod fairing solution Sonex offers is an aluminum sheet that requires some tricky bending, and even then it doesn’t look terribly good.  I decided to make one out of fliberglass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One night I bring in some modeling clay to form the mold.  Tristan joins me at the table and asks for some clay to play with.  Then Angelique sits down and asks for some too.  All three us play with clay.  It was fun.  The next day I layup the glass and epoxy.  When dry, I cut it and fit it.  Works great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the tail fairing I did, with only 3 layers of glass, I used 4 layers on these flap fairings which was probabaly overkill.  They are VERY sturdy, but weight quite a bit more than the ABS fairings from sonex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-16/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fairings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Charter Flights</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rivet Ramble</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/09/rivet-ramble.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rivet Ramble" /><published>2017-11-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/09/rivet-ramble</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/09/rivet-ramble.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-rivet-hole-prep&quot;&gt;Wing Rivet Hole Prep&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tedium of preparing all the wing skin hole has been continued and completed.  &lt;em&gt;Whew&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see in the picture how the front half of the holes are dimpled.  Unfortunately, the copper clecos kept popping out of these dimpled holes.  This was the clue #1 of the mistake I made.  More later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the skins all prepped and clecoed back in place on the wings it was time to rivet.  But wait… I should make sure the control surfaces fit, right?  And their push rods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-09/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dimpled Holes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ailerons-and-flaps&quot;&gt;Ailerons and Flaps&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had received the replacement flap skin (remember, I ruined that last one) so I assembled the right flap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I tried on the ailerons, they fit but motion was seriously limited.  The bolts that hold the counterweight were too long to fit through the cutout in the wing skin.  Rather than make the cutout bigger I decided to make the counterweight assembly smaller.  Replacing the normal nuts with thin special nuts I had left over, along with using a light washer instead of the regular, and cutting the tip of the bolt off removed about an inch from the width of the counterweight; small enough to fit right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was also a good time to address the lack of counterweight mass.  The top of the counterweight hits the top skin flush, and width was already a problem, so the bottom of the counter weight is where I could beef it up.  Check out the balancing rig below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cut some 5mm slices of lead to match the full width of the counterweight assembly.  This allowed for the thinnest profile possible with sufficient weight.  I drilled two holes vertically through the middle to attach with flush screws and a countersunk hole on the top so the nut would not add any height.  The screws had to be trimmed as well.  Then I shaved some lead off until it looked balanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-09/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Balanced Aileron&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the control rod pass-throughs had to be filed, but otherwise everything fits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rivetting&quot;&gt;Rivetting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are basically 3 difference rivets used on the wing skins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CCP-42 are short, round head blind (Cherry) rivets used on the ribs, hinge, and rear spar with is thin like the ribs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CCP-44 are a bit longer, still round head blind (Cherry) rivets used where the skin meets the main spar, which is thicker.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CCC-42 are short, countersunk head blind (Cherry) rivets for the dimpled holes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on the underside on the left inner panel, I started with the CCP-42 rivets and they went in great.  Then I moved on to spar using the CCP-44 rivets… you get a nice “thunk” reverberation sound when you rivet into the spar.  This lets you know you’ve got a solid hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riveting the dimpled holes was a bit more problematic.  Clue #2: The mandrels of the rivets were protruding out more often the usual after being pulled.  This is sign that maybe the shaft didn’t grab as deep as it should have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clue #3: A couple rivets were loose. Then I tried pushing from the inside and some just popped right out of the hole!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok… so the rivets aren’t holding in the dimpled holes.  I anticipated this problem because as I dimpled the holes I could see them expand.  So what now?  As I search for a solution I noticed something in the plans.  Off on the side, in the notes a sub-figure, there is it:  “Use a #31 or #32 drill bit, not a #30.”  Doh!  I already used #30 on ALL the dimpled holes.  Again… what now?  Obviously I can’t continue with rivets that fall out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so I could create a ribbon of aluminum sheet, line the inside of the ribs, used smaller countersunk rivets to hold it into place and then drill #30 holes that the rivets will grab on to.  But, jeez, that’s a heavy and clunky solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out there’s some rivets out there called Cherry Max rivets that are made in an oversized dimension, just a bit wider than #30 drill bits.  It also looks like they have the same size head as normal Cherry rivets.  They cost about 6x what normal Cherry rivets cost, but I think it’s a more elegant solution.  I ordered some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, might as well rivet the rest of the holes.  So I did.  That is, all except the top of the inboard skins.  These will get rivets last, once I’m done with the pitot, AOA, OAT plumbing.  I also left the aileron hinges unriveted so they could be removed when the controls get rigged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-09/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Wing Rivet Hole Prep</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tips and Dimples</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/06/tips-and-dimples.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tips and Dimples" /><published>2017-11-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/06/tips-and-dimples</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/06/tips-and-dimples.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-tips&quot;&gt;Wing Tips&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fiberglass wing tips are over-sized, as usual.  I ended up cutting 8” off the end to get maximum clearance through my garage door.  A metal strip is added to the inside of the fiberglass to add strength.  Still, there’s no significant structure holding the tips on… maybe 3/4” overlap with the wing skins… just enough for a line of rivets all the way around.  I can’t help but think that if the tips were much longer, they’d produce enough lift to rip themselves off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-06/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wing Tips&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tiedowns&quot;&gt;Tiedowns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fat nut plate just inside the bottom of the wing skin.  It’s from the AirWard tie down kit.  When desired, I can screw in an eye-bolt as a tie-down point.  You can see it is securely fastened to the spar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-06/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tie Down&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pitotaoa&quot;&gt;Pitot/AOA&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally settled on a location for the pitot/AOA tube.  Some modification of the Dynon install kit was required, but I feel like I have a much stronger mount then they prescribe.  It’s located just behind the main spar.  It’d be all the way at the end of the inboard wing but there’s an inspection hole there so it’s about 8” inboard from the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TODO: include picture of pitot mount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;oat&quot;&gt;OAT&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also placed the Outside Air Temperature sensor on the right wing just behind the pitot tube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;skin-hole-prep&quot;&gt;Skin Hole Prep&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rivet prep has begun.  Starting with the right inboard skin, I deburred, scrubbed with scotch brite, deburred spars and ribs,  dimpled the front skin holes, dimpled the front ribs, and clecoed it back in place.  This took almost 4 hours. I started the left side in the afternoon but didn’t finish because my rivet puller broke while using Sonex’s Super Simple Dimple Die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only four more skins to go.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Wing Tips</summary></entry></feed>
