<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://micahmartin.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-09-10T19:50:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com//</id><title type="html">OneX Build Log</title><subtitle>I'm building an airplane.  This is how it went so far.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Baffles</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/09/08/baffles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Baffles" /><published>2017-09-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-09-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/09/08/baffles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/09/08/baffles.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;engine-baffles&quot;&gt;Engine Baffles&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I never have to build engine baffles again.  ‘Nuf said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-09-08/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Baffles&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The K&amp;amp;N RC-1980 air filter seems to do the trick.  It attaches with a simple ring clamp and can be installed in such a manner so as to not interfere with the cowling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-09-08/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;K&amp;amp;N Air Filter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Engine Baffles</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Firewall</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/09/07/firewall.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Firewall" /><published>2017-09-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-09-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/09/07/firewall</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/09/07/firewall.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;exhaust&quot;&gt;Exhaust&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kit exhaust pipes are longer than needed.  They rest at an angle and I thought it’d look good to have them parallel with the fuselage, yet sticking out a bit to make sure the exhaust exits cleanly.  The cut line was a bit trikcy to get right, and then cutting with the grinding wheel was an experience that reminded me of the Orange County Choppers show where they fabricated choppers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-09-07/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Exhaust&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;firewall&quot;&gt;Firewall&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the firewall I added the ignitions, oil seperator, and battery (exact location still pending).  There’s still a few things to add but there should be plenty of room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-09-07/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Firewall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;baffles&quot;&gt;Baffles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After hiking this morning with Angelique, I had a bit of energy the afternoon to get started on the baffles for the engine.  Sonex provided a lazer but kit, but the fit is rough there’s plenty of modifications to be made.  These baffles feel a bit hackish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-09-07/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Baffles&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Exhaust</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Burp Elimination</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/09/05/burp-elimination.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Burp Elimination" /><published>2017-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/09/05/burp-elimination</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/09/05/burp-elimination.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;cowling&quot;&gt;Cowling&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took a great deal of time and care to get the cowling cut nicely.  Once it fit well, I added the camlocks (from an Aeroward kit) to fasten the top cowling to the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seams between the two halves were crooked (unavoidably) and I couldn’t leave it like that.  I made some micro-paste with epoxy and micro-bubbles to fill in the seams (see the first picture) and sanded them flush.  It turned out much cleaner I think.  There was also some sag in the bottom corners because I didn’t notice when I lined up the hinge rivets.  That part was probably a two man job but I did it solo.  So I reinforced the inside of the bottom corners with maybe 10 layers of fiberglass.  When dry, I sanded bottoms flush with the fuselage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-09-05/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Colwing Patchup&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-09-05/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cowling Complete&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;throttle--mixture-cables&quot;&gt;Throttle &amp;amp; Mixture Cables&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plans leave it up the builder how to run the throttle and mixture cables.  Not wanting to drill excessive holes in the longerons and support angles, I fabricated some brackets and mounted them to existing holes.  The AirWard kit came with some nice cable-safe firewall pass-throughs to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I drilled the hole for the gascolator line, I butchered that part of the firewall.  The steel is hard to drill, but very bendy.  The large drill bits catch and twist the thin steel.  So for the throttle and mixture pass-throughs, I added aluminum plates on the inside and out. This reinforcement made very clean holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rob helped me guide the cables through the bracket holes in which I had embedded rubber grommets.  This was an ordeal because the grommets kept popping out and we had to pull the cables out, re-insert the grommets, and try again.  The cables are a bit thicker where they bend and that’s where the brackets located, at the bends.  We eventually got it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-09-05/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cable Run&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning I connected all the cables to the controls and the AeroInjector.  The throttle was straight forward.  The mixture cable had a couple gotchas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, to cut the line to size you need to pull the inner cable out.  The mixture cable comes with the warning tag that says something like: “Do not poll knob out more then 3 inches or a ball bearning will pop out and the control will not function.”  Of course the first time I saw that I pulled it more than 3” and a tiny ball bearing did indeed pop out, and the knob no longer functioned.  I managed to find the ball bearing, get it back in and the the knob worked once again.  So today I was careful to catch the ball and no harm done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, with the mixture cable attached to the AeroInjector, the inner wire had a tendency to bend when I push the mixture full-rich or pull it (lean it), and the arm would not fully open or close.  With a washer to separate the wire from the mixture arm, and careful adjustment of the lock nut, the wire can swivel and avoid the bend.  Add to that some safety wire to hold the outer cable in place, and it resists tendency to bend even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-09-05/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;AeroInjector Cables&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fuel-lines--burp-elimination&quot;&gt;Fuel Lines / Burp Elimination&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see in the next picture the AirWard burp elimination system.  Aluminum tube running all along the edge of the firewall, an extra flex tube running to the AeroInjector, and a “T” junction that penetrates the firewall and connects to the fuel tank vent.  The principle is that high line will allow any air bubbles to escape and since it’ll be filled with fuel, it’ll add extra pressure to the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-09-05/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Burp Elimination&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bending and flaring these aluminum tubes was a new experience.  Pipe bending, cutting, and flaring tools are fairly inexpensive.  Those adel clamps hole the lines in place nicely.  I had to cut an extra little hole in the bottom cowling for the vent tube.  When I tried the cowling on again, it was blocked by air filter (I had installed it earlier today) which was rubbing against the bottom of the cowling.  Sigh.  I trimmed the rubber tube that connects the AeroInjector to the intake manifold to no avail.  After googling the problem, other builders had resorted to alternative air filters.  So I ordered a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00062YOIG/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o00_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;K&amp;amp;N RC-1980&lt;/a&gt; from Amazon.  Hopefully that works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the last two Oops fittings that go in the fuel tank.  A drain valve goes in one and the fuel level sensor will go in the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-09-05/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fuel Tank Oops Fittings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Cowling</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breadth First Building</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/30/breadth-first-building.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breadth First Building" /><published>2017-08-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/30/breadth-first-building</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/30/breadth-first-building.html">&lt;p&gt;In the past week, I started on several tasks, unable to complete any for various reasons.  However, much progress has been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sonex-build-visits&quot;&gt;Sonex Build Visits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Thursday I went to visit Denny and Jim at Deer Valley airport to check out their builds.  It’s always fruitful to see how other people build their planes.  I got plenty of ideas for improving my build.  And I got a better sense of how to proceed with the engine and electronic components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jim’s hangar was my first stop.  He’s been working on his Sonex for 12 years.  Maybe that’s because there are lots of distractions at the airport. At least three people stopped by within an hour to chat and check out the build.  Anyhow, Jim gave me a great tour and then got help from Denny to start up the engine and see how it ran.  Purred like a tiger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-30/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jim's Build&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the walk to Denny’s hangar I got a special treat.  Hoa, another Sonex owner was cleaning his beautiful bird.  He proudly presented his vinyl wrap job, which is truly nice.  He outsourced it and paid less than half what a paint job costs.  I still want to do my own wrap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-30/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hoa's Sonex&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denny’s Sonex has been flying for 9 years.  He did a wonderful job building it and he’s put over 700 hours on it since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-30/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Denny's Sonex&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon after the visits, I did a bit of work on the wing fold.  I wanted to better understand how they connect and fold.  While looking at it, I notices some flat heads protruding where the outboard spar attaches.  That’s not good.  So I took it apart and cleaned it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, I pulled out AirWard’s fuel shutoff kit and began work.  But I couldn’t figure it out so I emailed Dave.  He helped me realize that there was a missing part that I was able to pick up at the hardware store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;electrical-diagrams&quot;&gt;Electrical Diagrams&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received the Aircraft Wiring Guild over the week end and read it.  Although short, it spelled out a lot of things that were not obvious to me.  With what I learned, I was able to draw a couple schematics (below) of the electrical system I intend to build.  This was intense! Very details oriented.  What you can’t see is my spreadsheet detailing every wire; its gauge, ends points, terminators, and length.  It took about 2 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these, I was able to order all the wires, terminators, switches, and various electrical components I should need to wire everything together.  I fear it may take quite a while to complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-30/4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Main Electrical&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-30/5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Avionics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fuel-shutoff&quot;&gt;Fuel Shutoff&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem with the fuel shutoff kits is that Sonex has recently stoped building tanks with builtin ports and is including their Oops fittings instead.  The Oops fitting is a threaded, flanged tube that has to be inserted from the inside of the tank.  With a nut on the outside and rubber washers in and out, the Oops fitting seems very secure.  But Dave, from AirWard, hadn’t updated his kit to accommodate the Oops fittings so I had to get a bit creative to make it work.  But it does work, nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-30/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fuel Shutoff&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s two more kits for the fuel system.  The fuel system kit, which contains all the basic parts, and a kit to eliminate &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonexbuilders.net/viewtopic.php?f=33&amp;amp;t=1139&amp;amp;start=10&quot;&gt;the infamous “Burp” symptom of the AeroInjector&lt;/a&gt;.  The instructions for the burp kit were mind boggling.  I emailed Dave some more.  Eventually, after reading all the fuel system instructions multiple times and drawing diagrams, the system made sense and I could visualize it.  Great!  But the fuel components can’t interfere with the cowling, which hasn’t been installed yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cowling&quot;&gt;Cowling&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fuel system is on hold so I can work on the cowling.  Cutting and sanding fiberglass…. fun.  It cuts like butter compared to metal, but fiberglass particles go everywhere (ichy), and the chemical smells can’t be healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project brings back painstaking memories of the windshield.  The cowlings have to be cut in multiple places.  Most annoying is the engine rocker covers that stick out the side on a OneX.  The cowling won’t fit into place without the engine cover cut out.  And you don’t know where to make the cutout without fitting the cowling into place.  So it’s another game of install as much as possible, make tiny cuts, uninstall, cut, repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-30/7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bottom Cowling&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">In the past week, I started on several tasks, unable to complete any for various reasons.  However, much progress has been made.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Outboard Spar</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/23/outboard-spar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Outboard Spar" /><published>2017-08-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/23/outboard-spar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/23/outboard-spar.html">&lt;p&gt;I received all the avionics from Dynon.  That’s exciting.  It’s also exciting having the engine mounted.  But it’s all overwhelming.  There’s so many questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are all the parts that need to be mounted to the firewall?  Where do I put them all?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many things go on the panel and what the best way to lay it out?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where do all the fuel system components go?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oil system?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electrical system?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a few things I could easily attach to the engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oil cooler&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mufflers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Starter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spark plugs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did these on Monday (after watching the eclipse) and they can all be seen in the picture below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-23/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Engine Components&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aircraftwiringguide.com/&quot;&gt;Aircraft Wiring Guide by Marc Ausman&lt;/a&gt; book that I ordered from Lulu will help answer many of the questions.  It should arrive tomorrow.  I’ve also got an appointment to visit two other Sonex builders tomorrow morning, Denny Smith and Jim Armstrong.  I’m hoping I can get answers to my remaining questions from them and their builds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, yesterday and today I worked on the outboard spars.  These are the main supports for the outer parts of the wings that fold up.  These were a little easier than the main spar but my experience allowed me to complete them much faster.  Bucking rivets is exhausting so I quite a bit earlier than normal today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-23/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Outboard Spars&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">I received all the avionics from Dynon.  That’s exciting.  It’s also exciting having the engine mounted.  But it’s all overwhelming.  There’s so many questions:

  What are all the parts that need to be mounted to the firewall?  Where do I put them all?
  How many things go on the panel and what the best way to lay it out?
  Where do all the fuel system components go?
  Oil system?
  Electrical system?


There were a few things I could easily attach to the engine.

  Oil cooler
  Mufflers
  Starter
  Spark plugs


I did these on Monday (after watching the eclipse) and they can all be seen in the picture below.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Engine Mounted</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/18/engine-mounted.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Engine Mounted" /><published>2017-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/18/engine-mounted</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/18/engine-mounted.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;engine-mounting&quot;&gt;Engine Mounting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engine is mounted!  I recruited some help; specifically my friend Rob, my son Luka and his friends Caleb and David.  They were off to a high school football game so their friends Siri, Kayla, and Elly were over to eat first and car pool.  I had more help than I needed, at least I thought so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four of us guys lifted the engine while one helped line it up and insert bolts.  It took a few tries though.  The rubber grommets/bushings fit real tight and they were hard to get into place.  Then we realized that the bolts would only fit while the engine was off the mount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While pushing the engine in place, the plane kept rolling backwards.  Thankfully the girls where there.  They got behind the main spar and held the plane in place.  Everyone played a part and it was fortunate that they were all there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I swelled with a sence of accomplishment finally seeing the engine on the fuselage.  Special thanks goes out to my team of high spirited helpers.  Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-18/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Engine Mounted&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the engine mounted I can start to figure out where all the remaining controls, wires, cables, etc. need to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rear-spar&quot;&gt;Rear Spar&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While waiting on my engine helpers, I worked on some wing parts for a couple days.  The rear spar is now assembled.  Getting the subtle angled on the ends (not really visible here) was the only real tricky part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-18/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rear Spar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-ribs&quot;&gt;Wing Ribs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you see in the picture below is all the wing ribs for the inboard spar, and a couple for the outboard.  There’s more ribs, but all these were the same part number so I figured I’d work on them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boy was it tedious.  Mind-numbing.  16 nearly identical sets of parts each needing, clecoing, updrilling, de-burring, filing, scotchbriting, cleaning, and finally riveting.  What a relief when those were done…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-18/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wing Ribs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the wing parts are set aside for the time being.  I’ll start attaching them when I’m pretty much done working inside the fuselage so the wings don’t get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Engine Mounting</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flaps Controls</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/16/flaps-controls.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flaps Controls" /><published>2017-08-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/16/flaps-controls</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/16/flaps-controls.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;flaps-handle&quot;&gt;Flaps Handle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installed this yesterday.  Nothing much of interest to report.  I decided not to connect the rods so they wouldn’t get in the way when I work on the wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-16/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Flaps Control&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;elevator-trim&quot;&gt;Elevator Trim&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The elevator trim arrived right when I finished the flaps. The cable has to be routed from the instrument panel to behind the trim lever where the two rods meet.  After considering my options, I drilled some holes in the side fuselage beams, stuck some rubber gromets in there and rand the cable.  I think it looks decent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-16/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Trim Routing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These springs hold the elevator in a neutral position, and they’re connected to trim cable on the right side of the picture.  I’ll have to reconfigure the wire tension when I figure out where the trim knob will be mounted.  And I realized that my forward spring hole won’t work since the rear spar has to go there.  So I’ll relocate that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-16/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Trim Connection&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Flaps Handle</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Elevator</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/14/elevator.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elevator" /><published>2017-08-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/14/elevator</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/14/elevator.html">&lt;p&gt;Primary activity today: filing sheet metal holes.  I’ll explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up on the controls was the control stick and elevator rods.  The control stick mounts on the front side of the main spar with the stick right in the middle.  I was trying to figure out where to drill the holes to mount, when I saw some empty holes in the spar that match the control stick; but they were backwards.  Doh!  I riveted the spar together with the center beams backwards! Go figure.  I had flipped those beams over so many time trying to figure out which way was right.  No big deal.  Some fresh rivets to plug those holes, drilled new holes solved the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once installed, the stick was too tight and wouldn’t move easily.  That’s familiar.  Desassebling and sanding out the mount bushing did the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-14/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Control Stick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came the elevator connecting rods.  There’s two rods; one connects to the control stick arm, and the other to the elevator horn all the way aft.  In the middle they meet at this lever seen below.  I forget what’s it’s called.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front rod was short and easy to install.  The rear one… well remember how I said the bulkhead holes for the rudder cable where in the wrong place?  Well, not so.  Those were actually for the elevator rod and the plans warn that they may need to be enlarges to accommodate full motion of the elevator.  And boy did they.  I spent hours and hours under the plane, filing these holes. They holes had to widened just in get that 7” rod in place.  I lost hope on making nice circles, or ovals, or capsule shaped holes.  I would have had to remove too much material … I mean, how much of the bulk head can you take away before it looses structural integrity?  So I tried to leave as much material as possible which led to some less than aesthetic shapes, all the while making round edges so as to minimize stress risers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-14/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Elevator Lever&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of particular trouble was the aft fuselage where the control rod is bolted to the elevator horn.  This area is super tight and very crowded.  Even though I previously files the area to get the elevator to go all the way to it’s stop, the bolt and nut for the connecting rod were now interfering.  My battery powered dremel could get in there and trim away aluminum, but it’s a bit underpowered for metal work, and the battery drains quickly.  So I resigned to purchase a corded dremel today and that sped things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This picture is taken from inside the fuselage looking up and back toward the elevator horn at it’s stop.  Most of the ugly filed edges hidden here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-14/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Elevator Horn&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that’s left to complete the elevator controls is to install the cotter pins in all the bolts/nuts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Primary activity today: filing sheet metal holes.  I’ll explain.

Next up on the controls was the control stick and elevator rods.  The control stick mounts on the front side of the main spar with the stick right in the middle.  I was trying to figure out where to drill the holes to mount, when I saw some empty holes in the spar that match the control stick; but they were backwards.  Doh!  I riveted the spar together with the center beams backwards! Go figure.  I had flipped those beams over so many time trying to figure out which way was right.  No big deal.  Some fresh rivets to plug those holes, drilled new holes solved the problem.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rudder Pedals</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/11/rudder-pedals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rudder Pedals" /><published>2017-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/11/rudder-pedals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/11/rudder-pedals.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;avionics-research&quot;&gt;Avionics Research&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denny was kind enough to let me visit his build again and ask questions about avionics.  After doing research at Oshkosh and on the web, I’ve decided to go with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dynonavionics.com/skyview-se.php&quot;&gt;Dynon Avionics&lt;/a&gt; in a very similar configuration to Denny.  But there are hundreds of questions I had about the electrical/avionics system and Denny was kinds enough to answer them for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Denny's Panel&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rudder-pedals&quot;&gt;Rudder Pedals&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pedals are mounted using a phenolic blocks.  One on each side and one in the middle.  These had to be trimmed and sanded to fit.  Even after putting together whole rudder system, the pedals where too tight and I had to take it apart and sand down the holes more.  That made all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Both Pedals&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cable-adjusters&quot;&gt;Cable Adjusters&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aluminum bar is called the adjuster.  The location where the cable attaches does all the magic.  The plans give detailed instructions on how to calculate where to drill the cable hole, but they didn’t work for me. What I was left with was pedals that restricted eachothers movement and the ruder couldn’t even get close to its stops.  So I had to fabricate these parts from scratch and use my own technique to calculate the cable attach points.  Basically I started by moving the rudder to its full right stop.  Then positioned the left pedal as far aft as it would go and marked the attach point.  This would allow full right rudder and the left cable would  not restrict it.  Then I did the opposite for the right pedal.  This worked great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The springs pull the rudder to neutral when foot pressure is released.  At first I couldn’t get the springs tight enough to move the rudder.  This is when I realized I had to loosen the pedals by sanding the phenolic blocks.  With looser pedals, the springs could do their job.  The kit came with two long springs that had to be cut and bent to length, but I only used about 2/3 of one of the springs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rudder Padal Assembly&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pulleys&quot;&gt;Pulleys&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are six pulleys all together that keep the cable where it belongs and allow it to move easily.  Four of the pulleys I had build a while back when I first started on the fuselage.  The plans said it’d be easier to mount the rear pulleys at that point.  Not really.  And fortunately I hadn’t riveted them back then.  They had to be removed and I had to crawl inside the fuselage many times and in all locations.  There was no effort saved but I was pleased to have four fewer parts to fabridace this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Forward Pulley&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cable-run&quot;&gt;Cable Run&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulkheads have cutouts that would be ideal for rudder bale to run through.  Unfortunately, they’re in the wrong place.  I couldn’t believe it at first, but when I visited Denny, he complained about the same problem.  So extra holes had to be cut and existing holes elongated in the four center bulkheads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cable Run&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tail-cable-exit-holes&quot;&gt;Tail Cable Exit Holes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a puzzle to me how I’d calculate exactly where the cables would pass through the skin in the rear of the fuselage.  Fortunately, the plans give precise locations and sizes for these holes.  Unfortunately, they’re not prefect.  The cables rub up against the edges of the skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a good deal of time widening and elongating these holes to elimindate the chafing.  The left side was not terribly off.  The right side is still in progress.  I’ve already filed away an extra inch of skin and the cable is still chafing.  I’ll continue filing on monday and tidy up the edges so it looks intentional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Cable Exit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Avionics Research</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hydraulic Brakes</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/09/hydraulic-brakes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hydraulic Brakes" /><published>2017-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/09/hydraulic-brakes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/09/hydraulic-brakes.html">&lt;p&gt;As Hannah and Rob (family friends) walked by the garage last week as I was fabricating brake parts, we chatted and I mentioned that I didn’t know exactly how to install hydraulic brakes.  It turns out that Hannah’s dad (Vic) was coming to town. He’s handy with cars and knows about hydraulics.  So he came to help!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-09/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We mounted the master cylinder, no problem. Aside from the hydraulic lines, there was a brake handle to mount as well as a parking brake catch.  What was unclear what how much play there would be in the brake handle with fluid running to the brakes.  Without the fluid, there’s about 30° of play.  That seems excessive and far more than what’s drawn in the plans.  So the questions holding us up were this:  At what angle do we mount the handle to the master cylinder and at what distance does the parking brake catch get attached?  If we guess and get it wrong, we need to drill rivets and fabricate more parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, there was also the question of where to run the lines.  The master cylinder is inside the fuselage while the wheels are outside.  At least one hole has to be drilled so the lines can exit the fuselage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these reasons, Vic and I decided to temporarily run the hydraulic lines wherever was easiest, and then redo it properly when we knew more.  This is where Vic’s experience was priceless.  He knew exactly how to connect the lines and how to fill them with fluid, and bleed them.  I absorbed it all.  We also whipped up a temporary handle to operate the brakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bleeding the lines took the most finesse.  This involves removing all the air from the lines.  At the bottom of the brakes, there’s a little nut and when you loosen it, fluid (and air) flow out the bottom pulling fresh fluid from the master cylinder reservoir.  But those pesky air bubble don’t cooperate.  They prefer to flow upward and they find places to hide inside the brake housing.  It’s definitely a two man job.  One of us would get down by one of the brakes to lossen/tighten the bleeder, while the other would manage the brake handle to move the fluid and air around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about an hour, maybe more, we got all the air out and the brakes worked wonderfully.  As suspected, the play in the brake handle was much smaller that the 30° we saw without the fluid.  I was really impressed with how little motion was required to fully apply the brakes… and when you did, the wheels would not budge a bit!  So with that, we knew exactly where to drill the holes in the handle and where to mount the parking brake catch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks Vic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-09/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Working Brakes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day I tidied up the lines.  Before cutting the lines, I drilled all the holes needed and picked up some rubber grommets from Ace.  Although the plans don’t tell you where to drill the exit holes for the lines, they do tell you to run them along the back edge of the gear legs.  So I drilled two holes, one on each side of the fuselage right behind the gear legs.  A couple holes on each gear leg allow for clips to hold the lines in place and two more holes on an interior strut to keep the brake line in a safe place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dot 5.0 brake fluid is silicone based and really slippery, so tried my best to minimize the mess when I cut the filed lines, with moderate success.  I ran them through the holes and along their permanent path. Then Angelique was kind enough to come and help me bleed all the air out again.  It took about another hour.  I admit I like the pretty purple color of the hydraulic fluid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-09/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Clean Master&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-09/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Line on Gears&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">As Hannah and Rob (family friends) walked by the garage last week as I was fabricating brake parts, we chatted and I mentioned that I didn’t know exactly how to install hydraulic brakes.  It turns out that Hannah’s dad (Vic) was coming to town. He’s handy with cars and knows about hydraulics.  So he came to help!</summary></entry></feed>
