<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://micahmartin.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-06-07T20:28:34-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com//</id><title type="html">OneX Build Log</title><subtitle>I'm building an airplane.  This is how it went so far.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Nervous Procrastination</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/07/nervous-procrastination.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nervous Procrastination" /><published>2017-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/07/nervous-procrastination</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/07/nervous-procrastination.html">&lt;p&gt;Last week we were on vacation which was great.  In the mean time, all the parts I ordered were delivered and waiting for me.  So I continued with the canopy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-07/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frame&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frame was not too bad.  Cutting the canopy has been hard.  I’m worried that if I screw up too much, I have to order a new canopy and start from scratch.  I find myself walking around, finding reasons not to make the next cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using the DeWalt oscillating tool which is great.  It allows me to cut exactly where I want.  Many of the blogs I’ve read say you need two people to cut the canopy.  Not so with the oscillating tool.  One hand holds the canopy, the other cuts.  It’s very precise. So cutting where I want to cut is not a problem.  Knowing where to cut… that’s the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-07/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cutting Setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blogs suggested multiple cuts to make sure you don’t over do it.  I started with the front edge and did just that; made multiple cuts.  But I was left with and uneven edge.  Over and over I sanded the protruding edges and put the canopy back on to try it on.  When my arm became sore from sanding with the sanding block, I remember that the oscillating tool came with a sanding head.  That worked great.  The routine sped up.  Try canopy on; pull it off and place on saw horse; sand protrusions; repeat.  I marked the areas to work on with a sharpie and after a while, there were so many marks I couldn’t remember which was which.  So right after sanding, I applied some alcohol to wipe off the sharpie.  Then I noticed the cracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-07/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cracks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cracks!  How did those get there?  They weren’t big, but they definitely weren’t there before.  I concluded that it was the change in temperature.  The sanding got the surface hot, then a couple sprays of alcohol cooled it off, a lot; crack.  Fortunately, there was plenty of material on the rear of the canopy so I slid it forward about half an inch and started the process all over.  This may have actually saved me some time because my new cut was much smoother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The canopy is all curves.  Not in a good way.  You can’t know exactly where to cut because the canopy doesn’t fit.  You have to flex it to draw the line where you think you want to cut.  When you make the cut it fits totally different.  So, yeah, you do have to make multiple cuts.  Try to figure out how much of an edge you can cut without cutting too much.  Then try it on and figure out where to make the next cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently at the finer details of the cuts.  I drilled holes on the top front and back so I could cleco it to the frame.  But the frame is floating right now because it ultimately get’s fastened to the canopy and nothing else.  Double trouble.  Hopefully tomorrow I don’t screw it all up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-07/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Half Complete Canopy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Last week we were on vacation which was great.  In the mean time, all the parts I ordered were delivered and waiting for me.  So I continued with the canopy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Canopy Bows</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/25/canopy-bows.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Canopy Bows" /><published>2017-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/25/canopy-bows</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/25/canopy-bows.html">&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onexmike.org/canopy.html&quot;&gt;OnexMike’s technique&lt;/a&gt; didn’t work for me.  I lined up the bow with the template and pounded it with the rubber hammer and nothing happened except a lot of bouncing.  I’m not sure how he got it to work.  No problem.  I had a plan “B” which was to make a bending break.  That worked well.  Though it was a bit of a puzzle to figure out where exactly the bends were needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-25/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bending Break&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-25/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bent Bow&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kerry, Sonex support, insists that all my missing parts are my responsibility.  Oh well.  My solutions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Canopy Latch Handle:  I made one today with some extra aluminum angle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phenolic (plastic) for latch wear plate:  I tested the windshield plastic and found it to be very similar in strength and texture, So I used that instead.  See picture below.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Square tube: Used for the sides of the canopy frame.  Funny enough, the kit included enough of this to make one side, but not enough to make both.  I ordered more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Round tube: Used to make cross brace on back of canopy.  I ordered extra square tube for this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The picture below shows the rear latch wear plate that I installed.  Some extra aluminum spacers were added to remove some of the slack.  Sadly, the front wear plate wouldn’t fit because the throttle mount is in the way.  I had to cut it in half and use only one bolt to attach it.  Not sure how the plans missed this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-25/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Canopy Latch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">So OnexMike’s technique didn’t work for me.  I lined up the bow with the template and pounded it with the rubber hammer and nothing happened except a lot of bouncing.  I’m not sure how he got it to work.  No problem.  I had a plan “B” which was to make a bending break.  That worked well.  Though it was a bit of a puzzle to figure out where exactly the bends were needed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buckle Up</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/24/buckle-up.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buckle Up" /><published>2017-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/24/buckle-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/24/buckle-up.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;windshield&quot;&gt;Windshield&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got the windshield fastened today.  Lots of details were involved.  One problem I had was that the holes on the fuselage needed to be dimpled, but the holes were too big for the two dimple dies included.  But I figured out how to make one.  In the second picture you can see that my once soft computer programmer hands have been beat up and turned into tough mechanic hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-24/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finished Windshield&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-24/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dimple Die&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;seat-belts&quot;&gt;Seat belts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bolts for the seat belts (that weren’t included in the hardware kit &lt;em&gt;grrr&lt;/em&gt;) arrived today.  I had previously prepared the attach points so I bolted them on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-24/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Seat Belts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting on the canopy, I counted all the parts the plans call for that weren’t in the kit.  There are four.  Four parts that should have been in the kit.  So I emailed Kerry.  In the mean time I considered the canopy bows.  These are aluminum tubes that frame the inside of the canopy.   They come in rough curves but need to be shaped precisely and cut to length.  But how do you bend an aluminum tube to shape?  Well &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oy-raf.dk/&quot;&gt;Bjarne Jensen&lt;/a&gt; hit me up over email and suggested I look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://onex-svingenb.blogspot.dk/&quot;&gt;Bjoernar Swingen’s blog&lt;/a&gt;. I noticed he used play work templates. I thought I’d give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-24/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Canopy Bow Template&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I made the template, I realized that I’m gonne need something stronger than my hands to bend it.  So I found &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onexmike.org/canopy.html&quot;&gt;this post by good old OneX Mike&lt;/a&gt;.  I’ll give it a try tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Windshield</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Windshield</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/23/windshield.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Windshield" /><published>2017-05-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/23/windshield</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/23/windshield.html">&lt;p&gt;Don’t be decieved.  In the image below, the windshield and canopy are merely resting on top of the fuselage.  They are not fastened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the two, the windshield is supposed to be attached first.  Despite not fully understanding the plans, I proceeded like you would with a math problem; start with the knowns.  In this case, it’s the windshield strap.  I could see where it is attached and that it rests at a 60° relative to the longerons.  That I could do, so I did.  Then I put the windshield back on.  Ahhh… I could see it all now.  The windshield, an oversized sheet of glassy plastic with protective vinyl on both sides, overlapped the strap and it was obvious where to cut it.  And clearly it was too wide so I shaved a 1/4” off both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used my oscillating tool to make the cuts and it worked awesome.  Balancing it on my band saw was a scary thought and the hand held oscillating tool allowed me to cut it precisely while it rested on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the first cuts, it wouldn’t rest flush against the firewall in the front, no matter how I pushed it.  It was not obvious why.  I trimed some of the front corners but that didn’t help.  Then I tried removing the firewall/windshield strap.  That did it.  The clecoes where blocking it.  So I cut about 1/2” off the front and it fit wonderfully.  So I began drilling all the holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.airward.com/&quot;&gt;AirWard&lt;/a&gt; kit had instructions and hardware to use here so that the windshield is easily removable.  However, I got the gist of it and decided to go a bit off script.  With the big picture grasped, I know how to best craft it to my taste.  I should have it attached tomorrow, except for the fuel fill hole and cover… there’s supposed to be a 4.5” hole right in the middle of the windhield with an ugly aluminum plate covering it.  The plans don’t even say how to attach the aluminum plate.  I checked &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.airward.com/amelia/search.asp?advnav=&amp;amp;action=Search&amp;amp;store=&amp;amp;cat=10000781&amp;amp;subcat_10000013=10000781&amp;amp;ShowImages=&amp;amp;ShowDetails=&amp;amp;menuID=873~873&amp;amp;id=889&quot;&gt;AirWard and was pleased to see they have a solution for this&lt;/a&gt; that includes a transparent cover with easy access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-23/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fitting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Don’t be decieved.  In the image below, the windshield and canopy are merely resting on top of the fuselage.  They are not fastened.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Shields Up</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/22/shields-up.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shields Up" /><published>2017-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/22/shields-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/22/shields-up.html">&lt;p&gt;Since my last blog, I’ve begun a few separate tasks but missing hardware has delayed each until today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;spar-ends&quot;&gt;Spar Ends&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much to show here but I received the needed bolts and washers to finish assembling the spar tips and tighten all the bolts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;glare-shield&quot;&gt;Glare Shield&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been where most of the effort has gone in the past few days.  The glare shield is a sheet of metal that goes in front of the pilot and just under the wind shield.  It attaches to the upper firewall and the instrument panel in addition to the longerons.  The plans would have you rivet it all into place, never to be removed unless you want to drill out all the rivets.  Fortunately fellow OneX builder Denny Marick told me about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.airward.com/amelia/search.asp?advnav=&amp;amp;action=Search&amp;amp;store=&amp;amp;cat=10000759&amp;amp;subcat_10000013=10000759&amp;amp;ShowImages=&amp;amp;ShowDetails=&amp;amp;menuID=873~873&amp;amp;id=892&quot;&gt;Air Ward kit to make this glare shield removable&lt;/a&gt;.  It mostly involves installing nut plate where rivets would go.  Each nut plate requires 2 extra holes where rivets will hold the nut plate on. It adds a good deal more work, but it’s worth it in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-22/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Glare Shield Clecoed&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-22/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Glare Shield Screwed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fuel-tank&quot;&gt;Fuel Tank&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tank sits just below the glare shield, so it made sense to get that installed now.  It’s held up by two straps attached to the longerons, right where the glare shield attaches.  There was a problem here.  The fuel tank was bloated and wouldn’t fit in place. This is probably due to the change in temperature between freezing Oshkosh WI, from where it was shipped in January, to the 105° weather in Phoenix where I’m installing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used a trick that my dad used to use to crush milk jugs.  He’d put a bit of water into the empty gallon milk container and stick it in the microwave oven until the water was boiling.  Then he’s put the cap on and run it under cold water.  The milk container would shrink to a fraction of the size, taking less space in the trash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I boiled some water and poured it in the tank.  To get a little extra help I made sure to pour over the problem area hoping the heat would soften the plastic.  I put the cap on and the tank began to bloat more!  While pressing in on the problem area I ran the outdoor faucet over the tank and presto, magico, the tank contracted; not as much as the milk jug, just a bit.  Once cooled, I opened the cap and although the tank expanded a bit, the problem area was fixed and the tank fit perfectly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-22/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fuel Tank&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;windshield-and-canopy&quot;&gt;Windshield and Canopy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up is the windshield and canopy.  Today I fabricated and prepared most of the parts.  And I studied the plans, lots.  This is not and obvious assembly.  What makes it more challenging is that it’s ALL curves.  I’m going to see if I can find videos or blogs of other people who’ve done this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-22/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Windshield and Canopy PArts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Since my last blog, I’ve begun a few separate tasks but missing hardware has delayed each until today.

Spar Ends

Not much to show here but I received the needed bolts and washers to finish assembling the spar tips and tighten all the bolts.

Glare Shield

This has been where most of the effort has gone in the past few days.  The glare shield is a sheet of metal that goes in front of the pilot and just under the wind shield.  It attaches to the upper firewall and the instrument panel in addition to the longerons.  The plans would have you rivet it all into place, never to be removed unless you want to drill out all the rivets.  Fortunately fellow OneX builder Denny Marick told me about the Air Ward kit to make this glare shield removable.  It mostly involves installing nut plate where rivets would go.  Each nut plate requires 2 extra holes where rivets will hold the nut plate on. It adds a good deal more work, but it’s worth it in the end.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Place to Sit</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/17/a-place-to-sit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Place to Sit" /><published>2017-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/17/a-place-to-sit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/17/a-place-to-sit.html">&lt;p&gt;Lots to report:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wrap&quot;&gt;Wrap&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a test for going the vinyl wrap route as apposed to paint, I decided to wrap the hood of my car to get a feel for the process.  I got Luka to help me.  There was a learning curve.  It actually took us three attempts over 2 weeks and we ruined two wraps.  I had to order a new one with each failed attempt.  But in the end we got it as you can see in the first pic.  The carbon fiber texture and anthracite color is subtle, which is how I wanted it.&lt;br /&gt;
Lesson learned:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t stress about bubbles.  The 3M vinyl actually breathes allowing you to push bubbles out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peel off the backing while the wrap is upside down.  With your partner, flip it, gently stretch it and lay it down to cover the surface.  Getting the general layout right and smooth on the first try goes a long way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t over work the vinyl.  I found that it weakens as you work it.  Eventually it rips.  That’s bad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use a heat gun to restore the vinyls shape and integrity.  It’s cool material.  It remembers it’s shape.  So when it get’s stretched, maybe by your fingers, heat it and it will morph back into it’s original shape.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Watch lots of youtube videos.  There’s tons of techniques to learn from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-17/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wrapped Hood&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;spar-ends&quot;&gt;Spar Ends&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ends of the spars have several parts that get bolted on.  See second picture.  Of course hardware is missing from the kit so I had to order more from Aircraft Spruce.  Unbelievably I ran our of washers. The kit came with 20, FAR too few.  I ordered 150 more a few weeks ago.  But that still wasn’t enough so I ordered 400 more.  For now, most of the bolts are in place.   I’ll have to revisit this to put washers in place and swap out some bolts for the correct ones that are on order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-17/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spar Ends&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-seat&quot;&gt;A Seat&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was fun.  Once the seat was installed I couldn’t help but to jump in and try it out.  I just chilled for a few minutes in the half finished cockpit.  Although it looks tiny from the outside, it feels rather spacious on the inside.  Luka and Tristan tried it out too when they got back from school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-17/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tristan In Plane&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-17/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Luka In Plane&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;flap-retainer&quot;&gt;Flap Retainer&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This intricate part was a challenge to fabricate.  I will hold the flap lever, which has yet to be installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-17/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Flap Retainer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Lots to report:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rough Riveting</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/15/rough-riveting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rough Riveting" /><published>2017-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/15/rough-riveting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/15/rough-riveting.html">&lt;p&gt;All the solid rivets in the main spar have been bucked.  I can honestly say that I prefer the pull rivets over the solid rivets any day.  Why?  Bucking rivets is strenuous.  I began on Friday and it started fun.  But after a few dozen, my elbow was sore from holding the bucking bar, and I had a blister on hand from the hammer.  The hammer is a nice pneumatic gun, but all those impacts that their toll.  I had to quit after a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I recruited Luka and his friend Caleb to help me by holding the bucking bar.  After a few botched rivets, we got the hang of working together but time was tight and we only got about 100 rivets bucked before time ran out.  There are over 300 in the main spar. So I continued today and toughed it out until they were all done.  Whew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason the rivets that went through the angles, at the top and bottom, took much much longer to buck.  Maybe 5 time more blows with the hammer.  Where the angle tappered out, they got easy again.  Not sure why.  There must be something about the angles that absorbs the impacts, leaving less energy to squeeze the rivets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once complete, I managed to slide the spar into place.  This was no easy task either.  It required filing edges and some brute force with a rubber mallet to get it into place.  I was careful not to damage anything and in the end it fit nicely.  The brackets that attach the spar to the fuselage are in the works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-15/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spare in Plane&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-15/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First Rivets&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-15/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rivetted Spar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">All the solid rivets in the main spar have been bucked.  I can honestly say that I prefer the pull rivets over the solid rivets any day.  Why?  Bucking rivets is strenuous.  I began on Friday and it started fun.  But after a few dozen, my elbow was sore from holding the bucking bar, and I had a blister on hand from the hammer.  The hammer is a nice pneumatic gun, but all those impacts that their toll.  I had to quit after a while.

On Sunday I recruited Luka and his friend Caleb to help me by holding the bucking bar.  After a few botched rivets, we got the hang of working together but time was tight and we only got about 100 rivets bucked before time ran out.  There are over 300 in the main spar. So I continued today and toughed it out until they were all done.  Whew.

For some reason the rivets that went through the angles, at the top and bottom, took much much longer to buck.  Maybe 5 time more blows with the hammer.  Where the angle tappered out, they got easy again.  Not sure why.  There must be something about the angles that absorbs the impacts, leaving less energy to squeeze the rivets.

Once complete, I managed to slide the spar into place.  This was no easy task either.  It required filing edges and some brute force with a rubber mallet to get it into place.  I was careful not to damage anything and in the end it fit nicely.  The brackets that attach the spar to the fuselage are in the works.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Dilled, I Deburred…</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/11/i-dilled-i-deburred.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Dilled, I Deburred..." /><published>2017-05-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/11/i-dilled-i-deburred</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/11/i-dilled-i-deburred.html">&lt;p&gt;I drilled.  I deburred.  I got a repetitive stress injury.  At least I suspect I am.  It’s the deburring.  It puts a lot of pressure on the center of my palm and I think it’s the cause of a loss of sensitivity in my fingers in the last couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the spar, well most of it, all drilled and ready for deburring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps tomorrow I’ll get to solid rivets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-11/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spar All Drilled&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">I drilled.  I deburred.  I got a repetitive stress injury.  At least I suspect I am.  It’s the deburring.  It puts a lot of pressure on the center of my palm and I think it’s the cause of a loss of sensitivity in my fingers in the last couple of months.

Below is the spar, well most of it, all drilled and ready for deburring.

Perhaps tomorrow I’ll get to solid rivets.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Spar is a Bear</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/10/this-spar-is-a-bear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Spar is a Bear" /><published>2017-05-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/10/this-spar-is-a-bear</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/10/this-spar-is-a-bear.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday… I tried to decipher the plans and figure out how all the inboard spar pieces fit together.  In my head I had expected the spar to be just one or two long pieces of beefy metal.  Not so.  There’s got to be thirty pieces or so.  Once assembled they essentially form one long beefy chunk of metal, but with intricacies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I emailed Kerry and asked for pictures to help be understand.  He sent me some, but what really helped what a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onexmike.org/spar--inboard.html&quot;&gt;blog from a guy I know as Onex Mike&lt;/a&gt;.  This spelled it out for me with just the right pictures.  Thank Mike!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onces that was figured out, I had to drill holes in all the ribs, beams, supports and other stuff.  I finally finished today.  The shear quantity of material in this spar multiplies the work.  I’ll sheepishly admit that I thought I’d be done with the spar in a day or so.  Oh well.  One step after another. The picture below is the clecoed spar ready to updrill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-10/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inboard Spar, Clecoed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Yesterday… I tried to decipher the plans and figure out how all the inboard spar pieces fit together.  In my head I had expected the spar to be just one or two long pieces of beefy metal.  Not so.  There’s got to be thirty pieces or so.  Once assembled they essentially form one long beefy chunk of metal, but with intricacies.

I emailed Kerry and asked for pictures to help be understand.  He sent me some, but what really helped what a blog from a guy I know as Onex Mike.  This spelled it out for me with just the right pictures.  Thank Mike!

Onces that was figured out, I had to drill holes in all the ribs, beams, supports and other stuff.  I finally finished today.  The shear quantity of material in this spar multiplies the work.  I’ll sheepishly admit that I thought I’d be done with the spar in a day or so.  Oh well.  One step after another. The picture below is the clecoed spar ready to updrill.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hundreds of Holes</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/08/hundreds-of-holes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hundreds of Holes" /><published>2017-05-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/08/hundreds-of-holes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/08/hundreds-of-holes.html">&lt;p&gt;Friday was a busy day and I only got to work 4 hours fabricating parts for the main spar.  This morning I fabricated about 8 more parts.  Then the main spar webs.  These are 2 long, heavy pieces of aluminum that provide the main structure of the main spar.  They came prefabricated to the right shape with pilot holes, but the pilot holes are tiny, not even a pin hole.  But thank goodness they are there.  It would take a very long time to measure those 100’s of locations.  And without a pilot hole, there’s always minor errors in where the drill actually penetrates the metal and they can add up.  With the pilot hole, small though it may be, the drill bit tends to seek it out and follow it through making precisely located holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took hours to drill all those holes.  Note there are two layers in the picture, the bottom layer as more holes than the top.   I got a work out wrestling those parts to hold still in the right place on the drill press, 100’s of times. Then it took hours to debur.  I also filed the edges to remove stress risers.  Tedious work.  Now they are ready to mate with the the other spar parts and I’ll get to up-drill all the holes and debur them again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-08/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Main Spar Webs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Friday was a busy day and I only got to work 4 hours fabricating parts for the main spar.  This morning I fabricated about 8 more parts.  Then the main spar webs.  These are 2 long, heavy pieces of aluminum that provide the main structure of the main spar.  They came prefabricated to the right shape with pilot holes, but the pilot holes are tiny, not even a pin hole.  But thank goodness they are there.  It would take a very long time to measure those 100’s of locations.  And without a pilot hole, there’s always minor errors in where the drill actually penetrates the metal and they can add up.  With the pilot hole, small though it may be, the drill bit tends to seek it out and follow it through making precisely located holes.

It took hours to drill all those holes.  Note there are two layers in the picture, the bottom layer as more holes than the top.   I got a work out wrestling those parts to hold still in the right place on the drill press, 100’s of times. Then it took hours to debur.  I also filed the edges to remove stress risers.  Tedious work.  Now they are ready to mate with the the other spar parts and I’ll get to up-drill all the holes and debur them again!</summary></entry></feed>
