<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://micahmartin.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-12-13T19:08:46-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com//</id><title type="html">OneX Build Log</title><subtitle>I'm building an airplane.  This is how it went so far.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Xmas Wrapping</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/13/xmas-wrapping.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Xmas Wrapping" /><published>2017-12-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-12-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/13/xmas-wrapping</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/13/xmas-wrapping.html">&lt;p&gt;No, not wrapping presents yet.  Vinyl wrapping is has been this weeks activity.  But first…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;charter-flight&quot;&gt;Charter Flight&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I piloted another charter flight last Thursday.  KSDL (Sottsdale) -&amp;gt; KLAX (Los Angeles) -&amp;gt; KLAS (Las Vegas) -&amp;gt; KSGU (St. George, UT) -&amp;gt; KSDL.  Long day, great for flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sedona-hike&quot;&gt;Sedona Hike&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, Rob and Hannah Mooi flew up to Sedona with Angelique and I.  We had a delightful breakfast and scenic hike.  Awesome day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-13/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hike&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wrapping&quot;&gt;Wrapping&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outboard wings are quite long.  You can see in the first pic below the one skeet of grey wrap for the underside of the wing.  It’s all wrinkly at first, but looks really nice when “glassed” into place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-13/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Loose Wrap&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday I was able to get the tops of the right wing and both horizontal tail surfaces.  The right side of the design has these simple stripes that I think add a nice bit of character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lesson Learned&lt;/em&gt; - So… looking the wrapped wing, within 10”, you can see where I applied the micro-balloons.  It’s like, everywhere is glassy smooth, then a patch of mud, then more smooth surface.  When I had sanded down my patches, the surfaces looked silky smooth with an edgeless transition between the silver aluminum and white micro-paste.  Maybe the white color was the problem.  Once the vinyl when down, the edge of the patches became obvious and you can even see the grain of my sanding.  Every imperfection is pronounced.  &lt;em&gt;sigh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-13/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Right Side Wrapped&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Cherry Max rivets arrived Monday night, I was able to close up the wings on Tuesday.  Then I added more micro-paste to the new rivets lines, for consistency.  However, I used it sparingly this time. When dry, I applied full force sanding effort even pulling out the power tools… well just my oscillating tool with the sanding attachment.  Starting with a course grit, I sanded, then repeated with finner grit paper, then even finer.  Dust everywhere!  But, this time is was really smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With both wings fully wrapped, the most recent surfaces look much better then the original.  But there are still visibile imperfections that I didn’t notice before wrapping.  Clearly I need to improves my body work skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-13/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wings Wrapped&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also an attempt to wrap the top of the nose cowling.  But I eventually had to throw the whole sheet of vinyl away because it was over-worked, losing it’s adhesive.  Those compound curves!  After watching some vinyul wrap YouTube videos, I’ll try again by heating the vinyl first and start by stretching it around the curviest part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I also ran of our vinyl today and had to order more.  Fortunately I have plenty of scraps and smaller surfaces to wrap in the mean time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">No, not wrapping presents yet.  Vinyl wrapping is has been this weeks activity.  But first…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">End in Sight</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/06/end-in-sight.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="End in Sight" /><published>2017-12-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-12-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/06/end-in-sight</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/12/06/end-in-sight.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;mel-achievement-unlocked&quot;&gt;MEL Achievement Unlocked&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday and Friday last week I completed my multi-engine training and passed the checkride.  I’m now multi-engine certified.  This is mostly so I can start training for second in command in Elite Flights Jets’ Eclipse Jet for charter flights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;exhaust-wrapping&quot;&gt;Exhaust Wrapping&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple builders suggested insulating the exhaust to protect the inside of the engine compartment from high heat.  This fiberglass wrapping kit took months to arrive from Aircraft Spruce, but it finally arrived and the wrapping process was fairly painless, and quite messy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wrapped Exhaust&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fairing-wrapping&quot;&gt;Fairing Wrapping&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the small fairings are wrapped.  Those counter weight fairings were just too curvy for one piece of vinyl.  All the otheres are seamless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wrapped Fairings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-preparation&quot;&gt;Wing Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added some more micro-balloons to the wings because I noticed some spots I missed and incomplete transition from my last application.  The next day I sanded, and sanded some more.  The boys gave me some weird looks because I was covered in dust.  And my arm was SORE. Remember Karate Kid? Sand the Wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sanded Wing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bottom-tail-skin&quot;&gt;Bottom Tail Skin&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While waiting for the epoxy to dry, I started to work on the bottom tail skin.  This is essentially the last part to attach, because once on, the tail is virtually inaccessible.  However, I saw on AirWard that there was a kit to make to the tail accessible by using nut plates.  Although I didn’t buy the kit, I had enough nut plates to make the rear half unattached, around 50.  That leaves about 70 rivets for the remainder of the skin. Using nut plated for all the holes, to make a fully removable skin, was not workable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While installing nutplates, I observed that the rear two bulkheads could benefit from some bolts.  I don’t think rivets or nutplates would do these bulkheads justice.  So I installed the bolts and was content with a more secured frame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skin is all ready for rivets and screws… but I’ll wait a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tail-fairing&quot;&gt;Tail Fairing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attempted to wrap the tail fairing unsuccessfully.  The vinyl just doen’t stick to the composite parts like it does to metal and plastic.  Especially back side where there’s a very thin layer of clay, from the mold, that I just can’t seem to remove sufficiently.  They vinyl just won’t hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I ripped it all off and threw it out.  Then I went to ace and bought some white enamel spray paint.  This should help the vinyl stick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Painted Fairing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wrapped-underside-of-wings&quot;&gt;Wrapped Underside of Wings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the wrapping begin!  I wrapped the underside of both inboard wings.  These are the first solid parts of the plane to be wrapped.  This is also a key step in closing up the wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with large sheets of vinyl, upside down is tricky.  And it was a windy morning which added to the fun.  There’s a couple small boo-boos on the right side which I did first.  The left turned out better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wrapped Underside&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-fold-disaster&quot;&gt;Wing Fold Disaster&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While working under the right wing, I heard a loud boom and the whole airplane started to shake and rock side to side.  It took a moment for me to realize that the wind had blown the left wing past the balance point and it fell open.  Ouch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wind opening the wings had been a nightmare of mine which is why I installed the wing locks as soon as the outboard wings were first attached.  At the time, the wing’s didn’t close cleanly. Parts would interfere and get caught on eachother.  On a few occasions I unknowingly bent skins, clecoes, and other parts when folding and unfolding wings.  The leverage on the wings is intense!  I repaired all the damage of course.  But the thought of wind blowing the wings open with no one to resist the force and detect problems… Disaster!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this part of the build, I am folding and unfolding the wings multiple time every day so the wing locks were not used.  Foolish me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incredibly, I could not find any damage.  Not one hint of it!  This is one tough plane.  Still, the thought of that single hinge bolt taking all the force of the falling wing in an instant… I decided to replace it.  Fortunately I had spare bolts.  Even more fortunately, in the midst of replacing the bolt I noticed that I had not yet installed the cotter pins for these bolts.  Good thing.  Installing the cotter pins would not have been possible once the wings were sealed and the cotter pins are rather critical.  If I had forgotten them and closed the wings, I would have stared at the left over pins scratching my head and probabaly never realizing where they were supposed to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bolt that took the hit was fine too… at least I could not detect any deformity.  Disaster turned into good fortune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-interior&quot;&gt;Wing Interior&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the vinyl was on, I was able to install the pitot/AOA probe, and the AOT probe for the final time.  I wired the AOT probe and connected the pitot/AOA plumbing.  Then I started the final installation of the flap control rods, completing only the left before I had to come in for dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-12-06/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Connected Pitot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">MEL Achievement Unlocked</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Waitng For Rivets</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/28/waitng-for-rivets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waitng For Rivets" /><published>2017-11-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/28/waitng-for-rivets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/28/waitng-for-rivets.html">&lt;p&gt;The wings are on hold while I wait for rivets.  So in the mean time…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pitotstaticaoa&quot;&gt;Pitot/Static/AOA&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dynon’s installation kit for the Pitot/Static/AOA is quite convenient.  They use fasteners  where you simply push the platic tubing in, and it’s sealed. At least I hope it is.  So I ran all the plumbing, from the static ports on the side and the pito/AOA tube on the right wing, to the ADAHRS unit.  The pitot tube will still be removed so I can wrap the bottom of the wing without making a seam, so it’s not fully connected yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pitot AOA Plumbing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The static ports are installed in roughly the same place they are on most other planes, the rear sides of the fuselage.  Flush rivets hole them in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Static Vents&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;air-vents&quot;&gt;Air Vents&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denny Myrick suggested these air vents from Vans.  I felt terrible cutting holes into the sife of the plane, but I think they turned out okay.  Now I can get some fresh air in the cockpit on those hot Arizona days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Air Vents&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;elt&quot;&gt;ELT&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A while back I decided to get an ELT (Emergency Location Transmitter) even though it’s not required on a single seat experimental aircraft.  This is the smalled ELT I could find wwighting in at only a couple pounds.  It has to be installed on the left side of the fuselage, with the antenna exposed throuth the canopy so locations where limited.  I fabricated a mount attached to the bottom left longeron that should hold it steady enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ELT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wheel-pants-skins&quot;&gt;Wheel Pants Skins&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve put these off for a while.  Now’s the time.  I cut them to fit and got them mounted. Then I took them off to wrap them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared the wrapping the ailerons, these wheel pant were much more difficult.  It’s the compound curves.  The vinyl has to stretch and compress to fit smoothy and sometimes it just can’t do it.  At first I tried to wrap them with one piece of each color.  Eventually I gave up used three pieces.  It still took a good deal of time and effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They look good…. from a distance.  Up close you’ll notice some white lines between pieces, crooked corners, and sealing tape around all the edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wheel Pants&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;aeroinjector&quot;&gt;Aeroinjector&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aeroinjector had to be repositioned to get the needed fuel flow.  I cur the 45° silicone tube I had ordered and got it into position.  Of course the cowling not longer fit because the air filter was protruding too much.  After a few attempts, I figured out that the aeroinjector intake could fit all the way into the airfilter, about 2”, and by adding some material to the perimeter of the intake nozzle, fasten the air filter.  Then the cowling fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aeroinjector is held on by a hose clamp and silicone tube.  The seems a bit precarious, so I used some adel clamps and aluminum strips to add extra braces.  Now it is fastened to the engine mount and won’t be going anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-28/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aeroinjector&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">The wings are on hold while I wait for rivets.  So in the mean time…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cherry Fairing Balloons</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/16/cherry-fairing-balloons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cherry Fairing Balloons" /><published>2017-11-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/16/cherry-fairing-balloons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/16/cherry-fairing-balloons.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;charter-flights&quot;&gt;Charter Flights&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I complete my first charter flight as a captain, taking a couple from Las Vegas to Page AZ.  Then I did two more flights this week.  It was fun, but left less time to work on the OneX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cherrymax-rivets&quot;&gt;CherryMax Rivets&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aircraftspruce.com/catalog/hapages/cherrymax4.php?gclid=EAIaIQobChMIl4OEvKbE1wIVkqDsCh03VgMLEAQYASABEgL5KvD_BwE&quot;&gt;CherryMax rivets&lt;/a&gt; arrived over the weekend. These bad boys look significantly more complex than normal rivets, and they work…. Awesome!  Maybe too awesome actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they are the perfect size.  Yes!  They fill the oversized holes and, Dang, do they hold on tight.  The binded surfaces seem very secure, and the shafts break off flush with the head.  How cool is that?!  No holes in the center of the rivet. There were a couple new rivets that I wanted to redo, and this is where they are a bit too awesome.  I could not drill it out.  Without the hole in the factory head, I couldn’t get my drill bit to hold still.  The material seem harder as well.  It must be the cadmium. So I tried to drill it from the back, but the shaft protrudes and again I can’t get any drill action.  So, the moral here is:  Don’t mess up a CherryMax rivet.  You won’t get it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tested all the flush rivets I had previously installed.  about 90% of them fell out with little convincing from my drill.  All but a few were replaced with the CherryMax rivets.  Then I continued to rivet the outboard panel with the new flush rivets, and I ran out.  Oops.  I mis calculated how many I needed.  No problem, I can order more…. except they are not on backorder and will be for weeks.  &lt;em&gt;-sad face-&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-16/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CherryMax Rivets&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;micro-paste&quot;&gt;Micro Paste&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the flush rivets installed, the front wing skins became a bit puckered.  Just slight warping of the skin around each rivet.  It didn’t look terrible, but the goal of the flush rivets is laminar flow.  The puckered skin won’t help, and I want to be able to show off smooth, flat wings once they’re wrapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I mixed up some micro paste, epoxy with micro balloons, that is comparable to bondo.  This I applied to a couple rivet lines, then I mixed some more micro paste, then some more. Fortunately this stuff is really light.  I’ve probably applied about 12oz, volumetrically, to smooth our rivets and seems between surfaces.  Maybe that’s like a 1/4 pound.  I’ve still got a bit more to add.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopfully, the sanding is not too laborious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-16/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Micro Paste&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fairings&quot;&gt;Fairings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the fairing, and mounting surfaces and been prepared with the nutplates.  From left to right we have: aileron counterweight, aileron pushrod, rudder cable,  and flap control rod.  These are just left side fairings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only flap control rod fairing solution Sonex offers is an aluminum sheet that requires some tricky bending, and even then it doesn’t look terribly good.  I decided to make one out of fliberglass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One night I bring in some modeling clay to form the mold.  Tristan joins me at the table and asks for some clay to play with.  Then Angelique sits down and asks for some too.  All three us play with clay.  It was fun.  The next day I layup the glass and epoxy.  When dry, I cut it and fit it.  Works great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the tail fairing I did, with only 3 layers of glass, I used 4 layers on these flap fairings which was probabaly overkill.  They are VERY sturdy, but weight quite a bit more than the ABS fairings from sonex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-16/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fairings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Charter Flights</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rivet Ramble</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/09/rivet-ramble.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rivet Ramble" /><published>2017-11-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/09/rivet-ramble</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/09/rivet-ramble.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-rivet-hole-prep&quot;&gt;Wing Rivet Hole Prep&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tedium of preparing all the wing skin hole has been continued and completed.  &lt;em&gt;Whew&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see in the picture how the front half of the holes are dimpled.  Unfortunately, the copper clecos kept popping out of these dimpled holes.  This was the clue #1 of the mistake I made.  More later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the skins all prepped and clecoed back in place on the wings it was time to rivet.  But wait… I should make sure the control surfaces fit, right?  And their push rods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-09/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dimpled Holes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ailerons-and-flaps&quot;&gt;Ailerons and Flaps&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had received the replacement flap skin (remember, I ruined that last one) so I assembled the right flap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I tried on the ailerons, they fit but motion was seriously limited.  The bolts that hold the counterweight were too long to fit through the cutout in the wing skin.  Rather than make the cutout bigger I decided to make the counterweight assembly smaller.  Replacing the normal nuts with thin special nuts I had left over, along with using a light washer instead of the regular, and cutting the tip of the bolt off removed about an inch from the width of the counterweight; small enough to fit right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was also a good time to address the lack of counterweight mass.  The top of the counterweight hits the top skin flush, and width was already a problem, so the bottom of the counter weight is where I could beef it up.  Check out the balancing rig below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cut some 5mm slices of lead to match the full width of the counterweight assembly.  This allowed for the thinnest profile possible with sufficient weight.  I drilled two holes vertically through the middle to attach with flush screws and a countersunk hole on the top so the nut would not add any height.  The screws had to be trimmed as well.  Then I shaved some lead off until it looked balanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-09/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Balanced Aileron&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the control rod pass-throughs had to be filed, but otherwise everything fits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rivetting&quot;&gt;Rivetting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are basically 3 difference rivets used on the wing skins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CCP-42 are short, round head blind (Cherry) rivets used on the ribs, hinge, and rear spar with is thin like the ribs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CCP-44 are a bit longer, still round head blind (Cherry) rivets used where the skin meets the main spar, which is thicker.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CCC-42 are short, countersunk head blind (Cherry) rivets for the dimpled holes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on the underside on the left inner panel, I started with the CCP-42 rivets and they went in great.  Then I moved on to spar using the CCP-44 rivets… you get a nice “thunk” reverberation sound when you rivet into the spar.  This lets you know you’ve got a solid hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riveting the dimpled holes was a bit more problematic.  Clue #2: The mandrels of the rivets were protruding out more often the usual after being pulled.  This is sign that maybe the shaft didn’t grab as deep as it should have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clue #3: A couple rivets were loose. Then I tried pushing from the inside and some just popped right out of the hole!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok… so the rivets aren’t holding in the dimpled holes.  I anticipated this problem because as I dimpled the holes I could see them expand.  So what now?  As I search for a solution I noticed something in the plans.  Off on the side, in the notes a sub-figure, there is it:  “Use a #31 or #32 drill bit, not a #30.”  Doh!  I already used #30 on ALL the dimpled holes.  Again… what now?  Obviously I can’t continue with rivets that fall out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so I could create a ribbon of aluminum sheet, line the inside of the ribs, used smaller countersunk rivets to hold it into place and then drill #30 holes that the rivets will grab on to.  But, jeez, that’s a heavy and clunky solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out there’s some rivets out there called Cherry Max rivets that are made in an oversized dimension, just a bit wider than #30 drill bits.  It also looks like they have the same size head as normal Cherry rivets.  They cost about 6x what normal Cherry rivets cost, but I think it’s a more elegant solution.  I ordered some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, might as well rivet the rest of the holes.  So I did.  That is, all except the top of the inboard skins.  These will get rivets last, once I’m done with the pitot, AOA, OAT plumbing.  I also left the aileron hinges unriveted so they could be removed when the controls get rigged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-09/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Wing Rivet Hole Prep</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tips and Dimples</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/06/tips-and-dimples.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tips and Dimples" /><published>2017-11-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/06/tips-and-dimples</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/06/tips-and-dimples.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-tips&quot;&gt;Wing Tips&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fiberglass wing tips are over-sized, as usual.  I ended up cutting 8” off the end to get maximum clearance through my garage door.  A metal strip is added to the inside of the fiberglass to add strength.  Still, there’s no significant structure holding the tips on… maybe 3/4” overlap with the wing skins… just enough for a line of rivets all the way around.  I can’t help but think that if the tips were much longer, they’d produce enough lift to rip themselves off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-06/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wing Tips&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tiedowns&quot;&gt;Tiedowns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fat nut plate just inside the bottom of the wing skin.  It’s from the AirWard tie down kit.  When desired, I can screw in an eye-bolt as a tie-down point.  You can see it is securely fastened to the spar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-06/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tie Down&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pitotaoa&quot;&gt;Pitot/AOA&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally settled on a location for the pitot/AOA tube.  Some modification of the Dynon install kit was required, but I feel like I have a much stronger mount then they prescribe.  It’s located just behind the main spar.  It’d be all the way at the end of the inboard wing but there’s an inspection hole there so it’s about 8” inboard from the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TODO: include picture of pitot mount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;oat&quot;&gt;OAT&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also placed the Outside Air Temperature sensor on the right wing just behind the pitot tube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;skin-hole-prep&quot;&gt;Skin Hole Prep&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rivet prep has begun.  Starting with the right inboard skin, I deburred, scrubbed with scotch brite, deburred spars and ribs,  dimpled the front skin holes, dimpled the front ribs, and clecoed it back in place.  This took almost 4 hours. I started the left side in the afternoon but didn’t finish because my rivet puller broke while using Sonex’s Super Simple Dimple Die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only four more skins to go.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Wing Tips</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wing Skins</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/02/wing-skins.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wing Skins" /><published>2017-11-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/02/wing-skins</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/11/02/wing-skins.html">&lt;p&gt;Skins are all drilled.  The tricky part here was getting the ribs lined up and centered on the holes that needed drilling.  In many cases it was impossible to reach around the skins to adjust the rib positions.  That’s especially true when on my back under the wing.  Angelique was kind enough to help me for part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-11-02/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Skins Drilled&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much work still remains on the wings.  Need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install tie downs eye-bolts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pitot boom… Oh, I decided not to use the cheap pitot-static boom provided by Sonex and purchased the Dynon system which also provided angle of attack.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OAT - Outside Air Temperature sensor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install fiberglass wing tips&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Debur all holes (eek!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scrub and clean the skins&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dimple the front holes to promote laminar flow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install flaps and aileron control rods&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install access hole covers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rivet!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><summary type="html">Skins are all drilled.  The tricky part here was getting the ribs lined up and centered on the holes that needed drilling.  In many cases it was impossible to reach around the skins to adjust the rib positions.  That’s especially true when on my back under the wing.  Angelique was kind enough to help me for part of it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vinyl Wrapped Ailerons</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/10/30/vinyl-wrapped-ailerons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vinyl Wrapped Ailerons" /><published>2017-10-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-10-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/10/30/vinyl-wrapped-ailerons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/10/30/vinyl-wrapped-ailerons.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;ailerons&quot;&gt;Ailerons&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got the ailerons finished… mostly.  In order to properly balance them, they should be painted first, or wrapped in my case.  (side note: &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/RenbFgLZBNA&quot;&gt;Fascinating video showing why ailerons must have a counterweight&lt;/a&gt;)  So I get to try out the vinyl wrap!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My design calls for grey on the bottom and green on the top.  Here’s one wrapped and the other unwrapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-10-30/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Before and After&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right wing has a stripe that crosses the aileron.  The knifeless cutting tape works great!  Nice flush cuts between material.  One issue I have is the the top/bottom transition occurs right at the tail end of the aileron which is a pretty sharp curve.  The vinyl doesn’t like ending on a such a corner so I had to order some sealing tape.  I have liquid sealant for vinyl but reports say that it leaves a nail polish-like finish that doesn’t look so nice.  We’ll see how the tape works first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-10-30/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Right Aileron&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frustatingly, the counter weight isn’t heavy enough… even with the naked ailerons.  Grrrrr… I cut the lead ingot exactly the size the plans called for!  Now I’ll have to get the wings finished and figure out how I can add more weight to the aileron counterweights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-skins&quot;&gt;Wing Skins&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wing skins are time consuming.  Lots and lots of holes.  The skins need to be filed to fit properly.  Much work remains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-10-30/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wingos Skins&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Ailerons</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wing Work</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/10/25/wing-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wing Work" /><published>2017-10-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-10-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/10/25/wing-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/10/25/wing-work.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;wings-attached&quot;&gt;Wings Attached&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attaching the wings required some special tools; reamers.  These are like drill bits that make very precise sized holes.  I had ordered them from Amazon but one was the wrong size.  Fortunately Denny Myrick had them from his build and let me borrow it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-10-25/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wing's Attached&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are basically two bolts that hold the wing on.  A fat AN6 bolt on which the wings pivot on the upper spar, and a similarly fat pin that slides in a hole on the bottom.  The pin is attached to a lever to lock and release the wing.  The lever also controls a long pin that locks the rear spar in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-10-25/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wing Fold&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wing-locks&quot;&gt;Wing Locks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were a purchase from AirWard.  They required a bit of modification but perform a sturdy job of holding the wings up.  They cleverly make use of the holes and pins of the locking system&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-10-25/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wing Locks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;flaps&quot;&gt;Flaps&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before putting on the wing skins, I decided to install as much flaps and aileron controls as possible before they become entombed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I clumsily cut one of the flaps upside down and ruined the part.  Doh!  Another is on order from Sonex.  The left flap is complete and feels pretty solid.  The flaps will attach to the inboard wing sections and are a little over 2’ long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-10-25/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Flap&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ailerons&quot;&gt;Ailerons&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ailerons go along the complete outboard section and are nearly 6’ long!  Being so long, they require significantly more work…. lot of holes to drill, debur, etc…  They’re still under construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of note, they include a counterweight.  For this Sonex provided a ~20lb solid ingot of lead that needed to be cut.   You can see the smaller ingots bolted to the arms below. For months I feared the wear and destruction this ingot of lead would put on my tools.  Alas, lead is like butter when it comes to sawing and drilling.  Fascinating!  It’s massive rock-like appearance betrays it’s gentle workability.  In fairness, I’d assumed it was steel until I learned it was lead today.  Oh, lead does like to cease up on drill bits.  Using lots of oil is the lesson of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I have roughly 10lbs of smaller lead ingots left over.  I wonder what those could be used for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-10-25/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aileron Parts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Wings Attached</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Outboard Wing Frames</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/10/19/outboard-wing-frames.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Outboard Wing Frames" /><published>2017-10-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-10-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/10/19/outboard-wing-frames</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/10/19/outboard-wing-frames.html">&lt;p&gt;Last week was fall break and I had a great time with the family in Disney Land and Lego Land in California.  Upon getting back I continued work on the wing-fold parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aileron-control-bells&quot;&gt;Aileron Control Bells&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see in the first picture how these swivel paddles (not sure real name) mount to plates at the end of the spars.  This half goes on the outboard spar (the part that folds up) and will be connected to the ailerons.  The inboard paddles will connect to the control stick and translate control inputs to the ailerons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had both halves done, I lined them up and noticed that the paddles didn’t line up well at all.  The ball bearings rested on the very edge of the opposing paddles.  I doubled checked the plans several times, but I had followed them correctly.  Eventually I decided the plans were wrong and I was able to solve the problem by drilling out some rivets and putting the outboard paddles on the top of the swivel bell instead of the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-10-19/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wing Fold Fix&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wing-fold-panels&quot;&gt;Wing Fold Panels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the wing-halves meet, there are these plates that have soooo many rivets.  As I drilled, deburred and counter sunk all those holes, I had plenty of time to wonder why so many rivets would be needed.  You can see in the picture above that there’s not much structure to hold together; just two sheets. The best answer I could think of was: Why not?  The rivets do add strength to the layers and don’t add much weight.  But maybe it’s overkill.  Those extra rivers sure added a lot of labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-10-19/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wing Fold Installed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before attaching the outboard spars, the plans have you install the ribs, skin, and fiberglass tips.  I was going to get the folding joint secured first to save workshop room, but the rear spar participates in the fold-locking mechanism so I have at least have to get the ribs attached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I clecoed them all together I noticed that the inner most forward rib was about 1/8” shorter than the others.  There are spacers on almost all the ribs to make them equal length, but somehow the plans didn’t get it right… and no spacer was provided for this rib.  So again I went off script and made my own spacer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These assemblies are all riveted and bolted now.  Tomorrow I’ll see if I can get the spars attached and folding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-10-19/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wing Frames&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Last week was fall break and I had a great time with the family in Disney Land and Lego Land in California.  Upon getting back I continued work on the wing-fold parts.</summary></entry></feed>
