<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://micahmartin.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-05-08T20:41:58-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com//</id><title type="html">OneX Build Log</title><subtitle>I'm building an airplane.  This is how it went so far.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hundreds of Holes</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/08/hundreds-of-holes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hundreds of Holes" /><published>2017-05-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/08/hundreds-of-holes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/08/hundreds-of-holes.html">&lt;p&gt;Friday was a busy day and I only got to work 4 hours fabricating parts for the main spar.  This morning I fabricated about 8 more parts.  Then the main spar webs.  These are 2 long, heavy pieces of aluminum that provide the main structure of the main spar.  They came prefabricated to the right shape with pilot holes, but the pilot holes are tiny, not even a pin hole.  But thank goodness they are there.  It would take a very long time to measure those 100’s of locations.  And without a pilot hole, there’s always minor errors in where the drill actually penetrates the metal and they can add up.  With the pilot hole, small though it may be, the drill bit tends to seek it out and follow it through making precisely located holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took hours to drill all those holes.  Note there are two layers in the picture, the bottom layer as more holes than the top.   I got a work out wrestling those parts to hold still in the right place on the drill press, 100’s of times. Then it took hours to debur.  I also filed the edges to remove stress risers.  Tedious work.  Now they are ready to mate with the the other spar parts and I’ll get to up-drill all the holes and debur them again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-08/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Main Spar Webs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Friday was a busy day and I only got to work 4 hours fabricating parts for the main spar.  This morning I fabricated about 8 more parts.  Then the main spar webs.  These are 2 long, heavy pieces of aluminum that provide the main structure of the main spar.  They came prefabricated to the right shape with pilot holes, but the pilot holes are tiny, not even a pin hole.  But thank goodness they are there.  It would take a very long time to measure those 100’s of locations.  And without a pilot hole, there’s always minor errors in where the drill actually penetrates the metal and they can add up.  With the pilot hole, small though it may be, the drill bit tends to seek it out and follow it through making precisely located holes.

It took hours to drill all those holes.  Note there are two layers in the picture, the bottom layer as more holes than the top.   I got a work out wrestling those parts to hold still in the right place on the drill press, 100’s of times. Then it took hours to debur.  I also filed the edges to remove stress risers.  Tedious work.  Now they are ready to mate with the the other spar parts and I’ll get to up-drill all the holes and debur them again!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What a Mess</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/04/what-a-mess.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What a Mess" /><published>2017-05-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/04/what-a-mess</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/04/what-a-mess.html">&lt;p&gt;Three hours after beginning work I had everything cleaned up.  The fiberglass mold I laid out yesterday came off the plane very nicely.  The plane is not glued together in terrible ways… whew!  But boy was it a mess.  Wax, silicon film, clay, and epoxy all over the place.  These are not the type of products where a dry paper towel simply soaks up the mess.  I has to use a putty knife, mineral spirits, alcohol, scotch-brite, and dozens of paper towels. To make matters worse, I found dried epoxy finger prints on portions of the plane I didn’t protect with mold release agents (2nd pic).  I was wearing gloves and must not have noticed that I spilled some epoxy on my fingers.  It took a good portion of elbow grease to get those out.  The good news is that epoxy sticks to aluminum very well which means I can use some micro putty to create smaller permanent fairings on other joints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was all worth it.  After lots cutting the fairing piece and lots of sanding, it’s done.  See the first picture.  I love this solution far more than kit solution. Let me count the ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 piece instead of two&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8 screws instead of 20&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I installed a nut plate for each screw wherease the kit used sheet metal screws that thread into the sheet metal!?  They even warn you in the plans not to over tighten the screws less they strip.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All 3 joints have a fairing to improve aerodynamics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About 40 rivets are covered up, reducing drag.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better lines and no gaps between parts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cons? Well, a polished aluminum finish here won’t work… not that this matters for me, and there are already a bunch of fiberglass parts (like wing tips).  The weight is about the same as the aluminum covers.  My biggest concern is that it’s untested.  I think it’ll work great but I’m not sure how it’ll hold up to 150 knot winds.  Worst case scenario is that the wind rips it off and the plane will experience more drag.  Not a deal breaker.  I’m considering adding more glass to reinforce the part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued work on the wing bellcrank mounts that I started yesterday, but the plans are ambiguous.  It’s unclear exactly how some peices are supposed to be assembled.  Measurements are missing.  So rather then drill holes and pull rivets in the wrong place, I’m putting this task on hold until I know exactly how the parts are supposed to fit with the rest of the wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That brings me to the main spar.  The last picture shows the majority of material required.  I still have a few beams to cut.  This is going to be a hefty meld of metal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-04/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finished Fairing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-04/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finger Prints&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-04/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Main Spar Material&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Three hours after beginning work I had everything cleaned up.  The fiberglass mold I laid out yesterday came off the plane very nicely.  The plane is not glued together in terrible ways… whew!  But boy was it a mess.  Wax, silicon film, clay, and epoxy all over the place.  These are not the type of products where a dry paper towel simply soaks up the mess.  I has to use a putty knife, mineral spirits, alcohol, scotch-brite, and dozens of paper towels. To make matters worse, I found dried epoxy finger prints on portions of the plane I didn’t protect with mold release agents (2nd pic).  I was wearing gloves and must not have noticed that I spilled some epoxy on my fingers.  It took a good portion of elbow grease to get those out.  The good news is that epoxy sticks to aluminum very well which means I can use some micro putty to create smaller permanent fairings on other joints.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tail Fairing</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/03/tail-fairing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tail Fairing" /><published>2017-05-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/03/tail-fairing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/03/tail-fairing.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m not at all pleased with the way the tail panels came out.  See the first picture.  They required lots of bending to make them fit. It was non-trivial and I think I did a poor job.  This became an opportunity to try out some composite technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First was the play-dough, err modelling clay.  You can see a rough fill of the corners.  I left the panels in to give a shape to work around but they’ll go when it’s done.  Then I smoothed out the clay and removed the excess.  I’ve never sculpted much so this took a couple hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I was using the body of the plane as a mold, I had to take precautions to make sure the epoxy doesn’t stick to the plane.  This fairing will be removable so there’s access to the tail section.  I feared the epoxy would go everywhere and glue the plane in terrible ways.  So I took double precautions.  Mirror Wax, and Silicon spray. Both are mold release agents.  I really hope they do the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cut the fiberglass and peel pry.  Weighed it, and started mixing the epoxy.  Layer by layer I laid out the material and wetted it.  The glass is quite capable of handing the curves but the peel pry, not so much.  If I had to do it again, I’d cut small pieces to better fit the mold.  This was using one piece per layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While that sets, I bolted the engine mount and fabricated some parts for the wing fold assembly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-03/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Panels&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-03/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rough Clay&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-03/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Smooth Clay&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-03/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fiber&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-03/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Engine Mount&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">I’m not at all pleased with the way the tail panels came out.  See the first picture.  They required lots of bending to make them fit. It was non-trivial and I think I did a poor job.  This became an opportunity to try out some composite technique.

First was the play-dough, err modelling clay.  You can see a rough fill of the corners.  I left the panels in to give a shape to work around but they’ll go when it’s done.  Then I smoothed out the clay and removed the excess.  I’ve never sculpted much so this took a couple hours.

Since I was using the body of the plane as a mold, I had to take precautions to make sure the epoxy doesn’t stick to the plane.  This fairing will be removable so there’s access to the tail section.  I feared the epoxy would go everywhere and glue the plane in terrible ways.  So I took double precautions.  Mirror Wax, and Silicon spray. Both are mold release agents.  I really hope they do the job.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tail Gear</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/02/tail-gear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tail Gear" /><published>2017-05-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/02/tail-gear</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/02/tail-gear.html">&lt;p&gt;File!  Grind!  File!  That’s how the day began.  The horizontal tail and the rudder need to travel 25° up and down, left and right respectively.  Not only that, their lever arms need to hit squarely with the surfaces they meet at the end of their travel.  To achieve this meant lots of grinding with the dremel and filing with the files.  To my delight, I achieved the required travel on each surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon I made a trip to Ace, my home away from home it seems.  I needed the tiniest drill bit for the hinge cotter pins, and the biggest drill bit for the tail gear spring, which they didn’t have.  For the tail gear spring (a 2 foot long steel bar 5/8” in diameter) hole I drilled up the my biggest bit 1/2”.  Of course the spring didn’t fit.  I dremeled for a while and filed for a while trying to widen the hole without much success.  So I got creative and wrapped some emery paper (sand paper tape) around a drill bit, wedged it into the hole and spun the drill.  This was impressive.  Aluminum dust clouds sprung out from the hole and it made a nice smooth finish whereas the filing and dremeling looked sloppy. After adding a bit more tape a few times, the hole was the perfect size!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, I slid the spring through the hole and up to the mount in the rear of the tail.  It didn’t fit.  Of course I made several attempts to get it in but it was WAY too tight in the back of the tail.  I sighed, and drilled our a couple dozen rivets on the right skin to open up the area.  This worked.  But the mounts were installed too close together and the spring wouldn’t fit between them.  So I drilled those rivets and re-fabricated the mounts.  Even with the open skin it was very challenging to attach the spring bar.  To any future OneX builders, consider leaving the tail portion of one skin un-riveted, tempting though it may be to close it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried on the tail wheel. The push rod, used to steer the tail gear, was too short.  I figured I could cut 1/2 off the spring to make it reach.  Out came the grinding wheel and fireworks ensued.  It’s impressive how many sparks fly when you cut steel.  And that smell… mmmm… 4th of July!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then a 1/4” hole had to be drilled in to the tail wheel assembly and spring to hold them together.  Here’s what I learned:  Drill bits can tolerate aluminum.  But steel is the bane of drill bits.  It scars them rendering the poor bits dull and useless.  You know this happens when the bits just spins, smoke comes out of the hole, and everything becomes scolding hot.  You can’t just drill a 1/4” hole ya know.  You have to start small, drilling the hole with incrementally bigger bits.  I’m gonna have to go back to Ace soon and buy a new set of bits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tiny cotter pins go into each end of the hinges to lock the interior hinge rod in place.  The bit was so small it didn’t fit in my drill.  I had to wrap it with masking tape to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-02/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Opened Tail&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-02/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Gear&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-02/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hinge Ping&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">File!  Grind!  File!  That’s how the day began.  The horizontal tail and the rudder need to travel 25° up and down, left and right respectively.  Not only that, their lever arms need to hit squarely with the surfaces they meet at the end of their travel.  To achieve this meant lots of grinding with the dremel and filing with the files.  To my delight, I achieved the required travel on each surface.

In the afternoon I made a trip to Ace, my home away from home it seems.  I needed the tiniest drill bit for the hinge cotter pins, and the biggest drill bit for the tail gear spring, which they didn’t have.  For the tail gear spring (a 2 foot long steel bar 5/8” in diameter) hole I drilled up the my biggest bit 1/2”.  Of course the spring didn’t fit.  I dremeled for a while and filed for a while trying to widen the hole without much success.  So I got creative and wrapped some emery paper (sand paper tape) around a drill bit, wedged it into the hole and spun the drill.  This was impressive.  Aluminum dust clouds sprung out from the hole and it made a nice smooth finish whereas the filing and dremeling looked sloppy. After adding a bit more tape a few times, the hole was the perfect size!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tight Quarters</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/01/tight-quarters.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tight Quarters" /><published>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/01/tight-quarters</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/01/tight-quarters.html">&lt;p&gt;The tail is attached!  It all began last Friday.  Christoph, a colleague from 8th Light in London was in town for a conference.  After we flew to Sedona for lunch I convinced him to help me attach the tail surfaces to the fuselage.  We tried out the vertical tail and with a little finagling, got the gist of it figured out, though we didn’t fasten anything yet.  Then we tried on the horizontal tail and this is where it hit the fan.  It wasn’t fitting, at all.  The bottom skin was too long.  Then Christoph asked “Is it possible that the skin is up side down?”  Fear overtook me.  I checked the plans, made some measurements, and realized the truth. I had installed it upside down!  How could it be?  I checked them several times before installing and even wrote on the skins in sharpie to identify which way was up and which was was down.  Some how I got them backwards.  The horror!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this such a big deal?  The skin is held on with around 250 rivets.  Reversing it means drilling out all the rivits, flipping the skins and installing 250 new rivets.  As we’ve learned, rivets don’t always come out nicely.  If I could drill 9 out of 10 rivets successfully, which would be pretty good, that’d leave 25 wrecked rivet holes, not to mention hours of effort. The upside is that reversing the skins is possible because other than the slight difference in length where they meet the fuselage, that are symmetrical top to bottom. But I felt like crying.  Christoph and I called it a day and got some beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day I drove out to Deer Valley airport to fly with Denny (other OneX builder) in his RV-12.  He did a great job building that plane and we had a very nice flight.  But the point is that on the drive there and back I figured out a solution to my horizontal tail skins.  First, I could cut the bottom side (which was supposed to the top) to fit.  This would leave a 1/2 inch gap on the top.  But I had already considered crafting some fairings.  We learned a technique to make fairings out of composite materials (fiberglass) in the EAA workshops I went to in Las Vegas.  Not only would this cover the gap, but it would also make the plane more aerodynamic!  Double win!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I cut the skins to size.  Christoph helped me file it down, then file it some more, and again until it fit perfectly.  It turns out that had I installed the skins properly we would have had to file away a good bit of material anyway.  In the end, there was only a minor gap on the front top side, maybe 1/4 inch.  This was all very relieving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I continued fastening the tail surfaces, and I’m just about done.  That tail section is tight!  It has been very challenging to get the nuts on and tightened because nothing is directly accessible.  I was constantly reaching through inspection holes and between parts, and half the time my socket wrench was useless because it wouldn’t fit.  I had to go buy second set of wrenches to get it done.  And Luka had to come and help me reach parts that were impossible for me and my fat hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still work to be done here but I think the worst parts are done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-01/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Christoph With Tail&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-01/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Attached&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">The tail is attached!  It all began last Friday.  Christoph, a colleague from 8th Light in London was in town for a conference.  After we flew to Sedona for lunch I convinced him to help me attach the tail surfaces to the fuselage.  We tried out the vertical tail and with a little finagling, got the gist of it figured out, though we didn’t fasten anything yet.  Then we tried on the horizontal tail and this is where it hit the fan.  It wasn’t fitting, at all.  The bottom skin was too long.  Then Christoph asked “Is it possible that the skin is up side down?”  Fear overtook me.  I checked the plans, made some measurements, and realized the truth. I had installed it upside down!  How could it be?  I checked them several times before installing and even wrote on the skins in sharpie to identify which way was up and which was was down.  Some how I got them backwards.  The horror!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dimple Debacle</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/27/dimple-debacle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dimple Debacle" /><published>2017-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/27/dimple-debacle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/27/dimple-debacle.html">&lt;p&gt;Three trips to the hardware store today.  The first was to Ace to get a thread tap to make a threaded hole in the bellcrannk faces.  Those are done. They’re for translating control inputs from the inside part of the wing to the outside, and they’re pretty nifty.  Remeber the wings fold up.  There’s a outboard set of paddles and an inbourd set of paddles.  They lines up with eachother on a swivel.  When one rotates, it pushes the other making it rotate.  See the first pic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debacle.  Sonex includes two Super Simple Dimple Dies in the kit to dimple surfaces for flush rivets.  There’a big one for 1/8” holes and small one for 3/32” holes.  Basically they are two plates of hard metal. When you squeeze them together tightly with the sheet metal in the middle, they bend a little dimple in the sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each set comes with two nails that go through the center so that you can pull them together with a rivet puller.  The small set has skinny nails, understandably.  The first one broke on the first hole I dimpled.  It’s a lot of force required to bend the metal.  The second got me 6 more dimples and broke on the 7th. But it allowed me to finish the wheel pants connectors.  Today I had to dimple the tail mount to install some bolt plates, but I was out of skinny nails; specifically 4D-2” nails.  Earlier in the week I checked at the local Ace and they didn’t have any.  This moring I called Fountain Hill’s Ace and they told me they had two boxes in stock.  So I went over there (2nd trip of the day), but they didn’t have them.  The guys at the store concluded that their manufactureer just didn’t make 4D-2” nails, at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found some music wire that was the right diameter and is really strong, figuring we could bend a head on one end and cut it to length.  I got home and tried it out, several times.  It didn’t work.  The wire, strong as it was, would bend, or snap at the point where I bent a head on it.  My 3rd trip was to Home Depot to see if they had the 4D-2” nails.  They didn’t.  I bought a high temp map blow torch insted.  This allowed me to play blacksmith, hammering the hot wire against my vice making very creative bends.  They all snapped off.  Then I tried the simplest thing.  With red hot wire tip, I just smashed it flat. That worked.  &lt;em&gt;whew&lt;/em&gt;!  You can see all the attempts and the dimple dies in the second pic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third pic is the application of the dimples to attach those nut plates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-27/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bellcranks&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-27/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nail Fails&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-27/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Mount&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Three trips to the hardware store today.  The first was to Ace to get a thread tap to make a threaded hole in the bellcrannk faces.  Those are done. They’re for translating control inputs from the inside part of the wing to the outside, and they’re pretty nifty.  Remeber the wings fold up.  There’s a outboard set of paddles and an inbourd set of paddles.  They lines up with eachother on a swivel.  When one rotates, it pushes the other making it rotate.  See the first pic.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gear Girl</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/26/gear-girl.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gear Girl" /><published>2017-04-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/26/gear-girl</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/26/gear-girl.html">&lt;p&gt;My wonderful wife helped me today!  Together we installed the main landing gear.  It was a two man job.  I got on my creeper under the plane to drill and install the bolts, while she handed me the bits and put on the nuts from above.  What’s gonna work?  Team work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterward she had to go.  So I tried to figure out what I could work on next, while wating for parts to be delivered.  I decided the engine mount would be simple.  Alas, the bolts are missing from that hardware kit.  Sigh.  I ordered them and started working on the bellcrank, the interesting mechanism that translate controls between the wing segments were they fold.  For today, I got a bunch of angle parts fabricated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-26/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Angelique&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">My wonderful wife helped me today!  Together we installed the main landing gear.  It was a two man job.  I got on my creeper under the plane to drill and install the bolts, while she handed me the bits and put on the nuts from above.  What’s gonna work?  Team work!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Main Gear</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/25/main-gear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Main Gear" /><published>2017-04-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/25/main-gear</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/25/main-gear.html">&lt;p&gt;On to a task for which I have the parts: the main gear.  Based on advise from fellow Sonex builders I upgraded the brakes to Sonex’s AeroConversion hydraulics.  The first pic shows the intimidating amount of parts for the brakes.  To my surprise, it all came together quite simply.  So I attached the tires to the gear frame and then researched how to attach it all to the fusealge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are ten bolts that hold the gear onto the fuselage.  However, that big chunk of aluminum used for the gears (the strut?) doesn’t have any pilot holes. And it’s all curvy, so how do you find the exact center?  Well, I tried a few techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) First I laid a meter stick on top and marked the points where the flat top turned into a curve; where it seperated from the ruler.  The results seemed questionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Second I got a string and measured from each end of the strut, bottom to bottom and over the top.  Folding the string in half gave me center.  This seemed accurate but I noticed the string had some stretch to it.  I became worried that the the string’s elasticity would create an error.  So I looked for another method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) The second picture shows the strut balancing on the tip of aluminum angle. With use of a level to make sure it was pefectly balanced, and a carpenter’s square to make sure it was totally perpendicular, I had the center of gravity.  Since all the brakes and tire parts on each end were identical, I now had the center of the strut.  It matched the string’s measurement.  Turns out technique #1 was not good at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;designs&quot;&gt;Designs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checks out the design concepts my friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://nickmeccia.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;Nick Meccia&lt;/a&gt; did for me.  I love how they make the plane come alive!  I loved Transformers when I was a kid so I suggested a Decepticon theme.  These make me giddy with reminiscent joy.  Tough choice but my favorite is the second, Constructacon design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hydraulic Breaks&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Main Gear Assembly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/01.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design #1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/02.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design #2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/03.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design #3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/04.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design #4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-25/05.png&quot; alt=&quot;Design #5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">On to a task for which I have the parts: the main gear.  Based on advise from fellow Sonex builders I upgraded the brakes to Sonex’s AeroConversion hydraulics.  The first pic shows the intimidating amount of parts for the brakes.  To my surprise, it all came together quite simply.  So I attached the tires to the gear frame and then researched how to attach it all to the fusealge.

There are ten bolts that hold the gear onto the fuselage.  However, that big chunk of aluminum used for the gears (the strut?) doesn’t have any pilot holes. And it’s all curvy, so how do you find the exact center?  Well, I tried a few techniques.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bolted Box &amp;amp; Missing Hardware</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/24/bolted-box-missing-hardware.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bolted Box &amp; Missing Hardware" /><published>2017-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/24/bolted-box--missing-hardware</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/24/bolted-box-missing-hardware.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;blog-improvements&quot;&gt;Blog Improvements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’llbe the first to adminst that navigating this blog has been burdensome.  So I added some Next/Previous links to each page.  And the home page was getting VERY long, transferring far more bits than needed.  So I paginated the blog listing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog runs on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; using Jekyll.  I had originally tried other blog hosting sites, but with my coding background, working in an IDE and doing source control commits to publish new posts feels oh-so natural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These improvements veer off the treaded path of common Jekyll deployments, which means I had to do some yak shaving to get it all working.  I’m still not confident everything is 100% functional at the moment, but the site should be easier to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sustainable-aviation-symposium&quot;&gt;Sustainable Aviation Symposium&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I flew to San Francisco to attend the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sustainableaviation.org/sas2017/&quot;&gt;SA Symposium&lt;/a&gt;.  The topic is totally in line with my goals in aviation so I had to go.  The people there were incredible.  They had bold visions, ambitious goals, and they were achieving them!  Their long term vision, if I can sum it all up fairly, is to allow you to travel around your local town, county, or even state by going to the local air taxi station (similar to train station, or subway stop), hoping in an automated electric plane, and getting where you want to go faster than anything else can get you there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t bore you with names, but you can see who was there on the site.  I got to meet a lot of cool people.  There’s a pretty picture of Monterey Bay below from my flight back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sonex-progress&quot;&gt;Sonex Progress&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The box is bolted.  Almost 70 bolts went into the fuselage box today.  I could hardly believe it was that many.  But it was.  It took all morning an then some before they were all tightened.  And of course they didn’t all fit right away.  You can see in the first picture that they are packed in pretty tight on the firewall… the picture is just one of four corners like that.  In fact, some of the bolts interfere with each other and special skinny nuts are called for, however I couldn’t find them in the hardware kit.  I called Sonex and Kerry told me that the hardware kit is not complete and I need to go buy my own.  Thanks Kerry! Otherwise the fuselage box is all riveted and I’m ready to move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I referred back to the assembly tree at the front of the plans.  The last big branch of the tree is the wings.  But if I build the wings, I wouldn’t feel comfortable hanging them on a fuselage that is currently resting on saw horsed.  So I looked at the landing gear plans and it looks like that’s the next logical step.  But the tail gear requires that vertical and horizontal stabilizers are installed.  As I begin that assembly, I realize that I’m missing even more hardware from the kit.  In this case I think WBParts game me the wrong nut plates, in addition to Sonex not including the required nut in the kit list.  Grrrr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stuck a rivet in the extra hole I mentioned last week.  It’s a tiny SSC-24 countersunk rivet.  See pic.  I just used the deburring tool a bit more aggressively than normal to create the countersunk hole.  My mind is now at ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those building a OneX, the following hardware list is items that you may be missing too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AN960-10 washers.  Buy at least a 100 of these.  They’re called for all over the place and the kit only includes 20.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MS20464-1032 Fiberlock Thin Nuts.  12 or so.  These are the thin nuts to hopefully solve the interference joints.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MS21047-L4 Anchor Nut (Aircraft spruce: K1000-4). At least 3. The kits included these, but they gave me the wrong ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AN4-7A Bolt.  At least 3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-24/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bolts&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-24/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rivetd Extra Hole&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-24/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Box Rivited&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-24/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monterey Bay&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Blog Improvements</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deburring The Box</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/19/deburring-the-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deburring The Box" /><published>2017-04-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/19/deburring-the-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/19/deburring-the-box.html">&lt;p&gt;I wish I had enough interesting information to blog every day, but despite the last 17 hours of effort over the last two days, I’ve only got one new picture for you.  This is the fuselage box all updrilled, deburred, and ready to rivet/bolt.  Lots of bolts are called out to fasten the box together, which I suppose it for adding extra strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing of interest is that there were some needed holes that were impossible to drill with my hand drill and even the 90° chuck I got.  They are inside the box where the gear braces on the floor meet the vertical beams on the side walls, down in the bottom corner.  In the end I had to go to Home Depot and buy a Milewaukee angle bit that only holds hex bit, so I had to buy all new drill bits with hex ends.  It did the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a bunch of parts in this box assembly.  Over that past few days it was exciting to see the fuselage lengthen and look more and more complete.  And then, just when it all came together and fit perfectly, I had to take it all apart leaving me with just the tail I started with last week.  Onlookers are puzzled by the backward progress.  But I explain it’s a necessary step to prepare each piece for final fastening… and that is a time consuming process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: The plans for the side wall make you think that the skins are missing a pilot hole just below the wing.  When I noticed that I figured the skins pre-dated that plans (Kerry told me that was the case in other instances) so I added the hole.  That was a mistake.  The wing root covers the hole and the typical pop-rivet would cause it to bulge out.  So now I’m left with an extra hole on each side of the box.  It’s only visible from the inside, but I’ll always know it’s there and it’ll bother me forever.  Maybe I can countersink the hole with the deburring tool and put a flush rivet in there to put my mind at ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog entry brings me up to 300 hours of built time.  Only 200 hours left, according to Sonex marketing.  Yeah, right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-19/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Box Ready To Rivet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">I wish I had enough interesting information to blog every day, but despite the last 17 hours of effort over the last two days, I’ve only got one new picture for you.  This is the fuselage box all updrilled, deburred, and ready to rivet/bolt.  Lots of bolts are called out to fasten the box together, which I suppose it for adding extra strength.</summary></entry></feed>
