<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://micahmartin.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-14T21:32:02-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com//</id><title type="html">OneX Build Log</title><subtitle>I'm building an airplane.  This is how it went so far.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Elevator</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/14/elevator.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elevator" /><published>2017-08-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/14/elevator</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/14/elevator.html">&lt;p&gt;Primary activity today: filing sheet metal holes.  I’ll explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up on the controls was the control stick and elevator rods.  The control stick mounts on the front side of the main spar with the stick right in the middle.  I was trying to figure out where to drill the holes to mount, when I saw some empty holes in the spar that match the control stick; but they were backwards.  Doh!  I riveted the spar together with the center beams backwards! Go figure.  I had flipped those beams over so many time trying to figure out which way was right.  No big deal.  Some fresh rivets to plug those holes, drilled new holes solved the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once installed, the stick was too tight and wouldn’t move easily.  That’s familiar.  Desassebling and sanding out the mount bushing did the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-14/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Control Stick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came the elevator connecting rods.  There’s two rods; one connects to the control stick arm, and the other to the elevator horn all the way aft.  In the middle they meet at this lever seen below.  I forget what’s it’s called.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front rod was short and easy to install.  The rear one… well remember how I said the bulkhead holes for the rudder cable where in the wrong place?  Well, not so.  Those were actually for the elevator rod and the plans warn that they may need to be enlarges to accommodate full motion of the elevator.  And boy did they.  I spent hours and hours under the plane, filing these holes. They holes had to widened just in get that 7” rod in place.  I lost hope on making nice circles, or ovals, or capsule shaped holes.  I would have had to remove too much material … I mean, how much of the bulk head can you take away before it looses structural integrity?  So I tried to leave as much material as possible which led to some less than aesthetic shapes, all the while making round edges so as to minimize stress risers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-14/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Elevator Lever&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of particular trouble was the aft fuselage where the control rod is bolted to the elevator horn.  This area is super tight and very crowded.  Even though I previously files the area to get the elevator to go all the way to it’s stop, the bolt and nut for the connecting rod were now interfering.  My battery powered dremel could get in there and trim away aluminum, but it’s a bit underpowered for metal work, and the battery drains quickly.  So I resigned to purchase a corded dremel today and that sped things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This picture is taken from inside the fuselage looking up and back toward the elevator horn at it’s stop.  Most of the ugly filed edges hidden here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-14/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Elevator Horn&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that’s left to complete the elevator controls is to install the cotter pins in all the bolts/nuts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Primary activity today: filing sheet metal holes.  I’ll explain.

Next up on the controls was the control stick and elevator rods.  The control stick mounts on the front side of the main spar with the stick right in the middle.  I was trying to figure out where to drill the holes to mount, when I saw some empty holes in the spar that match the control stick; but they were backwards.  Doh!  I riveted the spar together with the center beams backwards! Go figure.  I had flipped those beams over so many time trying to figure out which way was right.  No big deal.  Some fresh rivets to plug those holes, drilled new holes solved the problem.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rudder Pedals</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/11/rudder-pedals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rudder Pedals" /><published>2017-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/11/rudder-pedals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/11/rudder-pedals.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;avionics-research&quot;&gt;Avionics Research&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denny was kind enough to let me visit his build again and ask questions about avionics.  After doing research at Oshkosh and on the web, I’ve decided to go with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dynonavionics.com/skyview-se.php&quot;&gt;Dynon Avionics&lt;/a&gt; in a very similar configuration to Denny.  But there are hundreds of questions I had about the electrical/avionics system and Denny was kinds enough to answer them for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Denny's Panel&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rudder-pedals&quot;&gt;Rudder Pedals&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pedals are mounted using a phenolic blocks.  One on each side and one in the middle.  These had to be trimmed and sanded to fit.  Even after putting together whole rudder system, the pedals where too tight and I had to take it apart and sand down the holes more.  That made all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Both Pedals&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cable-adjusters&quot;&gt;Cable Adjusters&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aluminum bar is called the adjuster.  The location where the cable attaches does all the magic.  The plans give detailed instructions on how to calculate where to drill the cable hole, but they didn’t work for me. What I was left with was pedals that restricted eachothers movement and the ruder couldn’t even get close to its stops.  So I had to fabricate these parts from scratch and use my own technique to calculate the cable attach points.  Basically I started by moving the rudder to its full right stop.  Then positioned the left pedal as far aft as it would go and marked the attach point.  This would allow full right rudder and the left cable would  not restrict it.  Then I did the opposite for the right pedal.  This worked great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The springs pull the rudder to neutral when foot pressure is released.  At first I couldn’t get the springs tight enough to move the rudder.  This is when I realized I had to loosen the pedals by sanding the phenolic blocks.  With looser pedals, the springs could do their job.  The kit came with two long springs that had to be cut and bent to length, but I only used about 2/3 of one of the springs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rudder Padal Assembly&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pulleys&quot;&gt;Pulleys&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are six pulleys all together that keep the cable where it belongs and allow it to move easily.  Four of the pulleys I had build a while back when I first started on the fuselage.  The plans said it’d be easier to mount the rear pulleys at that point.  Not really.  And fortunately I hadn’t riveted them back then.  They had to be removed and I had to crawl inside the fuselage many times and in all locations.  There was no effort saved but I was pleased to have four fewer parts to fabridace this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Forward Pulley&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cable-run&quot;&gt;Cable Run&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulkheads have cutouts that would be ideal for rudder bale to run through.  Unfortunately, they’re in the wrong place.  I couldn’t believe it at first, but when I visited Denny, he complained about the same problem.  So extra holes had to be cut and existing holes elongated in the four center bulkheads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cable Run&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tail-cable-exit-holes&quot;&gt;Tail Cable Exit Holes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a puzzle to me how I’d calculate exactly where the cables would pass through the skin in the rear of the fuselage.  Fortunately, the plans give precise locations and sizes for these holes.  Unfortunately, they’re not prefect.  The cables rub up against the edges of the skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a good deal of time widening and elongating these holes to elimindate the chafing.  The left side was not terribly off.  The right side is still in progress.  I’ve already filed away an extra inch of skin and the cable is still chafing.  I’ll continue filing on monday and tidy up the edges so it looks intentional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-11/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tail Cable Exit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Avionics Research</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hydraulic Brakes</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/09/hydraulic-brakes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hydraulic Brakes" /><published>2017-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/09/hydraulic-brakes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/09/hydraulic-brakes.html">&lt;p&gt;As Hannah and Rob (family friends) walked by the garage last week as I was fabricating brake parts, we chatted and I mentioned that I didn’t know exactly how to install hydraulic brakes.  It turns out that Hannah’s dad (Vic) was coming to town. He’s handy with cars and knows about hydraulics.  So he came to help!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-09/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We mounted the master cylinder, no problem. Aside from the hydraulic lines, there was a brake handle to mount as well as a parking brake catch.  What was unclear what how much play there would be in the brake handle with fluid running to the brakes.  Without the fluid, there’s about 30° of play.  That seems excessive and far more than what’s drawn in the plans.  So the questions holding us up were this:  At what angle do we mount the handle to the master cylinder and at what distance does the parking brake catch get attached?  If we guess and get it wrong, we need to drill rivets and fabricate more parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, there was also the question of where to run the lines.  The master cylinder is inside the fuselage while the wheels are outside.  At least one hole has to be drilled so the lines can exit the fuselage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these reasons, Vic and I decided to temporarily run the hydraulic lines wherever was easiest, and then redo it properly when we knew more.  This is where Vic’s experience was priceless.  He knew exactly how to connect the lines and how to fill them with fluid, and bleed them.  I absorbed it all.  We also whipped up a temporary handle to operate the brakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bleeding the lines took the most finesse.  This involves removing all the air from the lines.  At the bottom of the brakes, there’s a little nut and when you loosen it, fluid (and air) flow out the bottom pulling fresh fluid from the master cylinder reservoir.  But those pesky air bubble don’t cooperate.  They prefer to flow upward and they find places to hide inside the brake housing.  It’s definitely a two man job.  One of us would get down by one of the brakes to lossen/tighten the bleeder, while the other would manage the brake handle to move the fluid and air around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about an hour, maybe more, we got all the air out and the brakes worked wonderfully.  As suspected, the play in the brake handle was much smaller that the 30° we saw without the fluid.  I was really impressed with how little motion was required to fully apply the brakes… and when you did, the wheels would not budge a bit!  So with that, we knew exactly where to drill the holes in the handle and where to mount the parking brake catch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks Vic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-09/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Working Brakes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day I tidied up the lines.  Before cutting the lines, I drilled all the holes needed and picked up some rubber grommets from Ace.  Although the plans don’t tell you where to drill the exit holes for the lines, they do tell you to run them along the back edge of the gear legs.  So I drilled two holes, one on each side of the fuselage right behind the gear legs.  A couple holes on each gear leg allow for clips to hold the lines in place and two more holes on an interior strut to keep the brake line in a safe place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dot 5.0 brake fluid is silicone based and really slippery, so tried my best to minimize the mess when I cut the filed lines, with moderate success.  I ran them through the holes and along their permanent path. Then Angelique was kind enough to come and help me bleed all the air out again.  It took about another hour.  I admit I like the pretty purple color of the hydraulic fluid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-09/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Clean Master&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-09/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Line on Gears&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">As Hannah and Rob (family friends) walked by the garage last week as I was fabricating brake parts, we chatted and I mentioned that I didn’t know exactly how to install hydraulic brakes.  It turns out that Hannah’s dad (Vic) was coming to town. He’s handy with cars and knows about hydraulics.  So he came to help!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Controls &amp;amp; Hardware</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/07/controls-hardware.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Controls &amp; Hardware" /><published>2017-08-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/07/controls--hardware</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/07/controls-hardware.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;controls-parts&quot;&gt;Controls Parts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing with the controls, I started with the flaps.  Missing hardware prevented me from fastening the control stick to the mounting rod.  So I moved on to the aileron/stabilizer control and got the stick attached.  Then on to some pulleys, mounting brackets, and most everything required to put it on the fuselage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-07/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Controls Parts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hardware&quot;&gt;Hardware&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve complained about missing hardware a million times and I apologize.  We’re both fed up.  And the $6 shipping cost each time I order a couple bolts or nuts has been adding up.  Enough!  Today I spent several hours listing all the hardware call-outs in the plans (the pages I’ve yet to work on), taking inventory of the hardware I have on hand, and made a list of what’s missing.  $130 on Aircraft Spruce… Keep in mind that most nuts, bolts, washers, etc cost a few cents.  That should give you an idea of how much hardware is missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the nice presentation of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonexaircraft.com/eshop/cart.php?target=product&amp;amp;product_id=17532&amp;amp;category_id=441&quot;&gt;WB Parts OneX Hardware Kit&lt;/a&gt;, it is &lt;em&gt;severely&lt;/em&gt; lacking.  If you’re gonna build a OneX, I’d seriously consider &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.airward.com/amelia/search.asp?advnav=&amp;amp;action=Search&amp;amp;store=&amp;amp;cat=10000748&amp;amp;subcat_10000013=10000748&amp;amp;ShowImages=&amp;amp;ShowDetails=&amp;amp;menuID=882~882&amp;amp;id=885&quot;&gt;AirWard’s Hardware Kit&lt;/a&gt;.  It can’t be worse than WB’s kit; that’s for sure. And I’ve been very pleased with AirWard’s other kits in addition to their service.  When you email them, you get a response from Dave WARD.  Can’t beat that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Controls Parts</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Back to Work</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/04/back-to-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Back to Work" /><published>2017-08-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/04/back-to-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/08/04/back-to-work.html">&lt;p&gt;Summer was awesome but it’s time to get back to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;oshkosh-2017&quot;&gt;Oshkosh 2017&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luka and I flew up to Oshkosh on Sunday and camped next to the airplane. What a great time. We saw plenty of aircraft, of course.  For the first time I was able to attend lots of forums from which I learned a ton.  The Barenaked Ladies performed a great show on Monday.  But my favorite part was checking out all the homebuilds.  There’s soooo much variety!  And I was not previously aware how much influence Burt Rutan had on the homebuild world.  His designs are wonderfully unique and I love the canard style.  Now I’m thinking my next build will be a Long EZ, Cozy, or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-04/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Camp Site w/ Luka&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-04/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Baloons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luka and I headed home Wednesday but we didn’t get enough so we drove back with my dad on Thursday.  There was still so much to see!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-04/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Luka+Dad F16&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sonex-tour&quot;&gt;Sonex Tour&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At last I got to see Sonex’s home, and meet so many Sonex people that I’d been talking to on the phone.  We even got to go on a tour of their campus.  Great time.  What’s more, I got to check out a bunch of other Sonex builds that people brought to the show.  I was very curious to see how poor my work stood up to these experienced builders.  But I’m happy to admit that my workmanship stood its ground with the best of them… so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-04/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sonex Tour&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hydraulic-brakes&quot;&gt;Hydraulic Brakes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before starting the wings, I figure I should take advantage of the easy access to the cockpit and install controls.  So I started on the brakes.  Below is all that parts I fabricated for the brakes but I’m waiting on a bunch of hardware to finish the install.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-04/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hydraulic Brakes Parts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;access-panels&quot;&gt;Access Panels&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was just an easy task I was able to knock out.  The plans call for machine screws that thread into the skins.  I felt better using nut plates.  It took a bit longer but should hold up better over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-08-04/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Access Plate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Summer was awesome but it’s time to get back to work.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Loose Ends</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/14/loose-ends.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Loose Ends" /><published>2017-06-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/14/loose-ends</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/14/loose-ends.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I finished the canopy.  See below.  It’s… okay.  I’m not thrilled with how it turned out, but it’s good enough that I don’t feel the need to redo it.  My main gripe is that there’s two spots where it bows up, not fitting flush with the edges.  On the front edge, there’s a gap where air will certainly flood into the cockpit.  This I ameliorated with some foam tape which fills the gap and makes a good seal all around.  On the rear gap, well I’ll have to revisit that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-14/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finished Canopy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the canopy done, I wanted to tidy up some loose ends before summer break.  One item was the fuel tank refill hole that is cut in the wind shield.  You may remember that Sonex provided a 5” aluminum disk to cover the hole and eclipse the pilots vision!?  And I had purchased a clear cover kit from AirWard.  I installed that.  It’s much nicer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-14/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fuel Tank Refill Hole&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I removed the canopy, windshield, and glare shield.  Now I’ll have access to work on controls, wings, fuel system, power system, and electronics when I return from summer break.  The bird is looking bare again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-14/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Disassembled&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Yesterday I finished the canopy.  See below.  It’s… okay.  I’m not thrilled with how it turned out, but it’s good enough that I don’t feel the need to redo it.  My main gripe is that there’s two spots where it bows up, not fitting flush with the edges.  On the front edge, there’s a gap where air will certainly flood into the cockpit.  This I ameliorated with some foam tape which fills the gap and makes a good seal all around.  On the rear gap, well I’ll have to revisit that later.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Millimeters at a Time</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/12/millimeters-at-a-time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Millimeters at a Time" /><published>2017-06-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/12/millimeters-at-a-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/12/millimeters-at-a-time.html">&lt;p&gt;With the canopy roughly cut to size, I decided my best stratefy would be to cleco it to the frame.  This was a commitment because I couldn’t move the holes I had to drill.  Even though I couldn’t figure out if the canopy was the right size or shape, I figured it couldn’t be more than 1/4” off at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After spending tons of time sanding with little effect, I discovered that I could use the oscillating saw to shave off millimeters of material at a time.  Perfect!  That allowed me to cut the hinge side to fit.  With one side hinged, the “cut, try it on, cut” process became much quicker.  Not that it was easy.  It still took about ten more hours to get it in good shape.  But at least I didn’t have to take it off and prop it up on a saw horse for every cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow I’ll tidy up all the parts, install all the screws, and be thankful that part of the build is over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-12/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Canopy All Cut&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">With the canopy roughly cut to size, I decided my best stratefy would be to cleco it to the frame.  This was a commitment because I couldn’t move the holes I had to drill.  Even though I couldn’t figure out if the canopy was the right size or shape, I figured it couldn’t be more than 1/4” off at this point.

After spending tons of time sanding with little effect, I discovered that I could use the oscillating saw to shave off millimeters of material at a time.  Perfect!  That allowed me to cut the hinge side to fit.  With one side hinged, the “cut, try it on, cut” process became much quicker.  Not that it was easy.  It still took about ten more hours to get it in good shape.  But at least I didn’t have to take it off and prop it up on a saw horse for every cut.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nervous Procrastination</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/07/nervous-procrastination.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nervous Procrastination" /><published>2017-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/07/nervous-procrastination</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/06/07/nervous-procrastination.html">&lt;p&gt;Last week we were on vacation which was great.  In the mean time, all the parts I ordered were delivered and waiting for me.  So I continued with the canopy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-07/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frame&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frame was not too bad.  Cutting the canopy has been hard.  I’m worried that if I screw up too much, I have to order a new canopy and start from scratch.  I find myself walking around, finding reasons not to make the next cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using the DeWalt oscillating tool which is great.  It allows me to cut exactly where I want.  Many of the blogs I’ve read say you need two people to cut the canopy.  Not so with the oscillating tool.  One hand holds the canopy, the other cuts.  It’s very precise. So cutting where I want to cut is not a problem.  Knowing where to cut… that’s the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-07/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cutting Setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blogs suggested multiple cuts to make sure you don’t over do it.  I started with the front edge and did just that; made multiple cuts.  But I was left with and uneven edge.  Over and over I sanded the protruding edges and put the canopy back on to try it on.  When my arm became sore from sanding with the sanding block, I remember that the oscillating tool came with a sanding head.  That worked great.  The routine sped up.  Try canopy on; pull it off and place on saw horse; sand protrusions; repeat.  I marked the areas to work on with a sharpie and after a while, there were so many marks I couldn’t remember which was which.  So right after sanding, I applied some alcohol to wipe off the sharpie.  Then I noticed the cracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-07/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cracks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cracks!  How did those get there?  They weren’t big, but they definitely weren’t there before.  I concluded that it was the change in temperature.  The sanding got the surface hot, then a couple sprays of alcohol cooled it off, a lot; crack.  Fortunately, there was plenty of material on the rear of the canopy so I slid it forward about half an inch and started the process all over.  This may have actually saved me some time because my new cut was much smoother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The canopy is all curves.  Not in a good way.  You can’t know exactly where to cut because the canopy doesn’t fit.  You have to flex it to draw the line where you think you want to cut.  When you make the cut it fits totally different.  So, yeah, you do have to make multiple cuts.  Try to figure out how much of an edge you can cut without cutting too much.  Then try it on and figure out where to make the next cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently at the finer details of the cuts.  I drilled holes on the top front and back so I could cleco it to the frame.  But the frame is floating right now because it ultimately get’s fastened to the canopy and nothing else.  Double trouble.  Hopefully tomorrow I don’t screw it all up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-06-07/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Half Complete Canopy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Last week we were on vacation which was great.  In the mean time, all the parts I ordered were delivered and waiting for me.  So I continued with the canopy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Canopy Bows</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/25/canopy-bows.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Canopy Bows" /><published>2017-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/25/canopy-bows</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/25/canopy-bows.html">&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onexmike.org/canopy.html&quot;&gt;OnexMike’s technique&lt;/a&gt; didn’t work for me.  I lined up the bow with the template and pounded it with the rubber hammer and nothing happened except a lot of bouncing.  I’m not sure how he got it to work.  No problem.  I had a plan “B” which was to make a bending break.  That worked well.  Though it was a bit of a puzzle to figure out where exactly the bends were needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-25/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bending Break&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-25/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bent Bow&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kerry, Sonex support, insists that all my missing parts are my responsibility.  Oh well.  My solutions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Canopy Latch Handle:  I made one today with some extra aluminum angle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phenolic (plastic) for latch wear plate:  I tested the windshield plastic and found it to be very similar in strength and texture, So I used that instead.  See picture below.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Square tube: Used for the sides of the canopy frame.  Funny enough, the kit included enough of this to make one side, but not enough to make both.  I ordered more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Round tube: Used to make cross brace on back of canopy.  I ordered extra square tube for this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The picture below shows the rear latch wear plate that I installed.  Some extra aluminum spacers were added to remove some of the slack.  Sadly, the front wear plate wouldn’t fit because the throttle mount is in the way.  I had to cut it in half and use only one bolt to attach it.  Not sure how the plans missed this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-25/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Canopy Latch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">So OnexMike’s technique didn’t work for me.  I lined up the bow with the template and pounded it with the rubber hammer and nothing happened except a lot of bouncing.  I’m not sure how he got it to work.  No problem.  I had a plan “B” which was to make a bending break.  That worked well.  Though it was a bit of a puzzle to figure out where exactly the bends were needed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buckle Up</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/24/buckle-up.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buckle Up" /><published>2017-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/24/buckle-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/05/24/buckle-up.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;windshield&quot;&gt;Windshield&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got the windshield fastened today.  Lots of details were involved.  One problem I had was that the holes on the fuselage needed to be dimpled, but the holes were too big for the two dimple dies included.  But I figured out how to make one.  In the second picture you can see that my once soft computer programmer hands have been beat up and turned into tough mechanic hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-24/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finished Windshield&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-24/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dimple Die&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;seat-belts&quot;&gt;Seat belts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bolts for the seat belts (that weren’t included in the hardware kit &lt;em&gt;grrr&lt;/em&gt;) arrived today.  I had previously prepared the attach points so I bolted them on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-24/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Seat Belts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting on the canopy, I counted all the parts the plans call for that weren’t in the kit.  There are four.  Four parts that should have been in the kit.  So I emailed Kerry.  In the mean time I considered the canopy bows.  These are aluminum tubes that frame the inside of the canopy.   They come in rough curves but need to be shaped precisely and cut to length.  But how do you bend an aluminum tube to shape?  Well &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oy-raf.dk/&quot;&gt;Bjarne Jensen&lt;/a&gt; hit me up over email and suggested I look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://onex-svingenb.blogspot.dk/&quot;&gt;Bjoernar Swingen’s blog&lt;/a&gt;. I noticed he used play work templates. I thought I’d give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-05-24/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Canopy Bow Template&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I made the template, I realized that I’m gonne need something stronger than my hands to bend it.  So I found &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onexmike.org/canopy.html&quot;&gt;this post by good old OneX Mike&lt;/a&gt;.  I’ll give it a try tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Windshield</summary></entry></feed>
